<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Niniue to Englande, brought by the prophete Ionas vvhich newes in plainlye published in the godly and learned exposition of Maister Iohn Brentius folovving, translated out of Latine into Englishe by Thomas Tymme minister.</title>
            <author>Brenz, Johannes, 1499-1570.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843943</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843943</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8711</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8711)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 523:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Niniue to Englande, brought by the prophete Ionas vvhich newes in plainlye published in the godly and learned exposition of Maister Iohn Brentius folovving, translated out of Latine into Englishe by Thomas Tymme minister.</title>
                  <author>Brenz, Johannes, 1499-1570.</author>
                  <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 81 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Denham, dwelling in Pater noster rowe, at the signe of the starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1570.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 2789.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jonah --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Newes from Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue to Englande, brought by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Ionas: Which newes is plainlye publiſhed in the Godly and learned expoſition of Maiſter Iohn Brentius folowing, tranſlated out of Latine into Engliſhe by Thomas Tymme Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The ſilent tongue, the liſtning eare,</l>
               <l>which harkeneth after newes:</l>
               <l>With ſtaring eye, and gaping mouth</l>
               <l>this title makes me vſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Henrie Denham, dwelling in Pater noſter rowe, at the ſigne of the ſtarre. 1570.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:2"/>
            <head>To the right honourable <hi>Lord Willyam Cobham, lord</hi> Warden of the cinque Portes: Thomas Tymme wiſheth Neſtors yeares, increaſe of honor, with preſeruation of deſired health.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE CVRTEOVS BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, the noble vertue, but ſpeciallye the godlye zeale (Right honourable) which fame and report cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefieth me to be in you, hath kindled ſuch an earneſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in me, that my rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and baſe ſtate ſtayeth mee nothing at all, to dedicate this ſimple worke vnto you. For I know that Nobilitie, gratefully accepteth at others hands ſlender giftes, and of ſmall reputation, according to their habilitie that offer the ſame.</p>
            <p>Artaxerxes, his good acceptation of a handfull of running water, made mee thus bolde, to offer this Pamphlet to your honour as a token of my good will: hoping that as he thought no diſdain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the one, ſo you wil not take ſcorne of the other. Let me craue therefore this one thing, at your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours handes, that the baſeneſſe of my tranſlation of the learned Brentius procure not you, to refuſe
<pb facs="tcp:8711:3"/> the patronage and defence of my ſlender woorke. Which as I know vndoubtedly ſhall neuer coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruayle your worthineſſe: ſo do I aſſuredly hope that it may be a proofe of my good will, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The worthy Prophete IONAS, deſerueth a worthie perſonage to be his defence and garde, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt ſcoffing Lucian, and fretting Momus.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if your honor refuſe not, but vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, to take the ſame vpon you (as I perſwade my ſelfe you will, weying the giuers intent, and ſeing that theſe are partly the firſt fruites of his trauaile) you ſhall not onely purchaſe immortall prayſe of others: but I alſo ſhall be incouraged, and anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to greater, and waightyer attemptes: which I ſhall no ſooner atchieue, but you ſhall be a witnes of my indeuours, and a rampire to my exploytes.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing boldly required your honors aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and tediouſly moleſted your eares with cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces, leauing now at length to abuſe your friendly pacience, I end: wiſhing to your honor the increaſe of Nobilitie, with a moſt happie eſtate, and after this lyfe, the gladſome ioyes of the euerlaſting lyfe to come.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Beneficium dando accepit, qui digno dedit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Orator Thomas Tymme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:3"/>
            <head>The tranſlator to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>THe Merchant man that often ſayles</l>
            <l>vpon the rockie ſeas,</l>
            <l>Hath oftentimes for recompence</l>
            <l>the gaine that doth him pleaſe.</l>
            <l>The Fiſher man that caſtes his net,</l>
            <l>and layes his bayted ginne,</l>
            <l>Doth truſt at length by happie hap,</l>
            <l>his pray of fiſhe to winne.</l>
            <l>The Plowman eke that ſowes his ſéede</l>
            <l>on ſoyle, with toyle, for gaine,</l>
            <l>The Winters trauaile being paſt,</l>
            <l>doth reape the riped graine.</l>
            <l>If Plowman then, and Fiſher too,</l>
            <l>haue ſtedfaſt hope for gaines,</l>
            <l>As recompence for their ſore toyle,</l>
            <l>and daily pinching paines:</l>
            <l>Why ſhould not I as well as they,</l>
            <l>by paine ſome profite haue,</l>
            <l>Since that my Muſe as recompence</l>
            <l>moſt iuſtly doth it craue?</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:4"/>
            <l>The which good reader thou ſhalt graunt,</l>
            <l>if that thou take in woorth:</l>
            <l>This ſimple Pamphlet at hir hande</l>
            <l>which ſhe hath nowe ſet foorth.</l>
            <l>And helpe to moſell <hi>Momus</hi> mouth</l>
            <l>and bridle <hi>Zoilus</hi> chappes,</l>
            <l>Which like a Curre ech willing Wight</l>
            <l>with curriſh fanges he ſnappes.</l>
            <l>This done, well quighted is hir paine,</l>
            <l>hir recompence is had,</l>
            <l>And if thereby ſhée doe the good,</l>
            <l>ſhée is excéeding glad.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Tymme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:4"/>
            <head>¶The Preface of Iohn <hi>Brentius vpon the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of Ionas.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle Paule wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Corinthians, of the meeting and comminge togither of the Church, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth all thinges to be done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to edifying. When ye come togither (ſayth he) euerye one of you hath a ſong,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a reuelation, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng. Seing therefore it is determined that wee muſt come togither certaine dayes in the weeke: I will take in hande (by the aſſiſtance of Gods holy ſpirite) for our exerciſe at that time the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Prophet Ionas, to the ende wee may be godly occupied and exerciſed in this oure meetinge. For wee come not togither in the Church to trifle and playe, but we come to the ende we might be inſtructed in the worde of the Lorde. Neyther are we created by God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by the precious death and bloudſhedding of Chriſt, to the ende we ſhould ryot, lyue in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and giue our ſelues to all kinde of filthye pleaſure, but we are created and redeemed to the ende we might glorifie God by our lyfe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. We haue taken in hande therefore to expounde the prophecie of Ionas, that by this prophecie we maye be admoniſhed, of our office, dutie and calling.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:5"/>
            <p>And although the booke of this prophecie be very ſmall, yet notwithſtanding, it contayneth an excellent and famous hyſtorie. Firſt of all therefore, we will declare, who was this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ionas: Then what, and how great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie his propheſie hath: And laſt of all, we wil ſhewe the argument, and what the ſumme of the doctrine contayned in this booke, is.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there are many, which thinke, and iudge the prophete Ionas to be the ſonne of the widowe of Sarepta, which receyued and fedde Elias in the time of famine: but their iudgement is neyther likely nor probable. For, of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ionas, we haue mention made in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth Chapter of the fourth booke of Kinges,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.</note> how that Ieroboam king of Iſrael, reedified his decayed Kingdome, accordinge to the worde of the Lord which he ſpake by the prophet Ionas, the ſonne of Amithay, which was of Gathhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher. By the which it appeareth, that hee made not only the ſermon contayned in this booke, but many other notable and famous ſermons, which are not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For he preſerued by his ſermons, two of the moſt excellent kingdomes that were. Excellent was the kingdome of Iſraell: but in the time of Ionas it was a decayed and ruinous kingdome, by impietie and inuaſion of enimies. Ionas therefore, being ſtirred vp by the holye ghoſte, exhorteth the people to repentaunce, and incourageth king Ieroboam valiauntlye to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his common welth: promiſing, that God will ſende a time of mercie, wherein he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his kingdome. And ſo in deede it came to paſſe, that the coaſt of Iſraell, from the entring of Hemath, vnto the ſea of the wilderneſſe, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb facs="tcp:8711:5"/> by the goodneſſe of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>Famous alſo was the Citie of Niniue, for in it, was the greateſt Monarchie of the whole worlde. But the Lorde had determined to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye the Citie of Niniue, from the face of the earth. Yet notwithſtanding, Ionas ſaued the ſame by his ſermon. Wherefore, ſeeing Ionas by hys ſermons ſaued ſuch two excellent kingdomes, he is not to bee counted among the common ſort of men, but euen among the chiefeſt Prophetes that haue beene, eyther before his time, or ſince.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt conſider the certaintye, and aucthoritie of this booke. The Church as yet, neuer reiected or refuſed this booke: but haue accounted the ſame among thoſe, which wee call Canonicall bookes of holye ſcripture, and which haue Eccleſiaſticall, and heauenlye teſtimonies. Furthermore, we haue our ſauiour Chriſt (as concerning this matter) a ſufficient teſtimony and witneſſe, as may appeare by the .xij.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 12.</note> Chapter of Mathew, where he alledgeth the example of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas for his reſurrection, affirming, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Ionas out of the Whales bellye, was a type of the ſame. Furthermore, Chriſt preferreth the Niniuets, before the Iſraelites, bicauſe the Niniuets repented at the one onelye ſermon of Ionas, and the Iſraelites woulde not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto the Lorde by many ſermons.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if euer any man did, or ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after doubt of the aucthoritie, truth, and certaintie of this booke, Chriſt by his teſtimonie, hath ſo confirmed the ſame, that though an Aungell came from heauen teaching the contrary, he ought not to be beleued.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, we muſt knowe the argument or
<pb facs="tcp:8711:6"/> ſumme of this prophecie, in the which certayne perticuler places are noted.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt place conteyneth the ſeueritie of the wrath of God towardes all ſuch as walke diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediently in their calling. Ionas was a Prophet which was moſt acceptable vnto god, and which before, had done notable things in Iſraell, and by his ſermons had preſerued the kingdome of the ſame: notwithſtanding, when hee fled and was diſobedient to his calling, he was caſt by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of God, into the Sea. An example of Gods ſeuere puniſhment worthye to bee noted. The lyke we haue of Saule,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note> who, diſobeying the commaundement of God, reſerued part of the pray of Amelecke, for the which diſobedience hee was rent from his kingdome. Another example we haue of the prophete,<note place="margin">3. <hi>King.</hi> 13.</note> whom the Lion ſlue by Gods appoyntment for his diſobedience. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it is ſayde, to obey, is better than ſacrifice, and to hearken is better than the fat of Rammes.<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſeconde place conteyneth the wonderful, and inſpeakeable mercy of God, by the which, he commonly deliuereth all thoſe which call vpon him in truth. Ionas was caſt into the ſea, and deuoured of the Whale. And although he coulde not be ſaued and deliuered naturally: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, by the diuine power and clemencie of God, he is ſupernaturally, and miraculouſlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered. This miracle, to certaine worldly wiſe men, and contemners of the worde of God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ridiculous, and like vnto olde wyues tales.</p>
            <p>And amongſt all others, ſcoffing Lucian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtirred vp of Sathan the Deuill, the father of lyes, to obſcure, diſcredit, and deride this miracle, hath written a booke intituled, <hi>De veris narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8711:6"/> that is, a booke of true narrations: in the which, hee maketh mention of certaine men, which being in a ſhip, were ſwallowed vp ſhippe and all, of a Whale, in the which Whale (ſayth he) there were Mountaynes, woods, and Cities, to the which the men arriued with their ſhippe, and had great delectation there. This fonde fable ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee inuented by Lucian, to deride the Chriſtians, which beleeue the ſtorie of Ionas to be true. But this and many other ſuch are deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Deuill and his miniſters, to deride, and deface, true, and godly myracles.</p>
            <p>But let vs vnderſtand, that this myracle was done in deede, and that it hath heauenly teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to proue and ratifie the ſame, as we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie declared. God which created heauen, and earth of nothing, and which rayſed, and will rayſe the dead to life, could alſo for a time, ſaue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue Ionas in the whales belly. Let vs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therefore this myracle to be a declaration of the power and clemency of God, and an example alſo of the reſurrection of Chriſt, and of all the godly alſo to euerlaſting lyfe, as hereafter GOD willing ſhall be declared.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The thirde place conteyneth the doctrine of repentaunce. There haue beene many which haue denyed to ſinners after their fall any hope of gods grace. And there are manye, which when they haue ſinned, perſwade themſelues that there is no way of ſaluation left vnto them. Here therefore there are two examples of repentaunce propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs: The one in the Prophete Ionas, who although he fell into diſobedience: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, repenting he is receyued into Gods fauour againe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:7"/>
            <p>The other, in the Niniuets, who although they had greatly ſinned, inſomuch, that they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued eternall deſtruction and damnation: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, repenting, they are receyued into Gods fauour, and preſerued with their Citie. Let vs therefore turne to the Lorde by repentaunce, being perſwaded that the Lorde will receyue vs, and that the Aungels in heauen ſhall reioyce ouer our repentaunce.</p>
            <p>Thus (gentle Reader) I haue declared, who this Prophet Ionas was, what aucthoritie this booke hath, and which are the ſpeciall places of this booke. The which, if thou well obſerue and note, they will profite, to the nouriſhing of the feare of God, to the encreaſe of fayth, and to the bringing forth of true obedience, which are the moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruice of God.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8711:7"/>
            <head>¶ A godly expoſition of <hi>the Prophet Ionas.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The first Chapter.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE VVorde of the Lorde came vnto IONAS the ſonne of Amithai, ſaying:<note place="margin">The text.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and get thee to Niniue that great ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie, and preache vnto them howe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir wickedneſſe is come vp before mee.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THe Scripture of the olde Teſtament, doth often and verie much teſtifie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat God in times paſt, hath ſpoken with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Patriarches, and Prophets: As ſayth the Apoſtle Paule in his Epiſtle to the Hebrues.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</note> God in times paſt diuerſly and many wayes ſpake vnto the fathers, by Prophetes. Let vs therefore vnderſtande and knowe, howe and after what maner God hath reuealed his will to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches
<pb facs="tcp:8711:8"/> and Prophets.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Sometimes he ſpake with them, by ſending Aungels viſiblye vnto them:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gene.</hi> 18.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample we haue in the booke of Geneſis, where we reade that Aungels came vnto Abraham, in the likeneſſe and ſhape of men.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gene.</hi> 19.</note> Alſo there came Angels vnto <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oth,</hi> which brought him out of <hi>Sodome</hi> before it was deſtroyed. And ſo an Angell appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red viſibly vnto <hi>Zacharias</hi> the father of <hi>Iohn:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 1. <hi>Math.</hi> 1.</note> to the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> likewiſe, and to many other.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Sometimes, God ſpake vnto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the voice of an Aungell inuiſibly. And ſo he talked with <hi>Moſes</hi> out of the buſhe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.</note> where <hi>Moſes</hi> hearde the voyce of an Angell ſpeaking in the perſon of God, but ſawe no Aungell. So the Aungell in the perſon of God recited the lawe, in the Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. <hi>and</hi> .20.</note> the which voice was heard of more than ſixe hundreth thouſand men, but they ſawe no man: as appeareth by the wordes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying. You hearde the voyce of his wordes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deuter.</hi> 4.</note> but you ſawe no forme or ſhape at all. So God ſpake by an inuiſible Aungell vnto <hi>Samuell.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 3.</note> So (I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8711:8"/> thinke) alſo that the Lorde ſpake to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> from the mercye ſeate as appeareth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y this text.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.</note> And from thence I will teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vnto thée, and will common wyth thée, from of the mercie ſeate.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Oftentimes he ſpake vnto the fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y dreames:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Daniel.</hi> 7. <hi>Geneſi.</hi> 37.</note> as maye appeare by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Nabuchadnezar, Ioſeph,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Oftentimes by the <hi>Ephod</hi> of the Prieſt which ſhone with precious ſtones, the which ſtones (as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſayeth) when God aunſwered the demaunde of the Prieſt by his <hi>Ephod,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioſephus lib. <hi>3.</hi> de an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquita. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> excelled and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted their accuſtomed ſhyne and brightneſſe: but when God refuſed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, the precious ſtones remayned in their woonted glorie, nothing altered or chaunged.</p>
                  <p>That the Lorde did ſometimes aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere by <hi>Ephod,</hi> it is apparaunt by the ſcriptures, as by the thrée and twentie and eight and twentie Chapters of the firſt booke of Kings.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Oftentimes he ſpake to the fathers by viſions,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1.</note> the whiche viſions the holye
<pb facs="tcp:8711:9"/> ghoſt by ſecrete inſpiration reuealed and interpreted.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 And oftentimes he ſpake vnto them without viſions, onely by the ſecret inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſpirite.</p>
                  <p>But howſoeuer it pleaſed God to ſpeake, and talke with this our Prophete <hi>IONAS</hi> there is no mention made, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it greatly neceſſary to be knowne. For it is ſufficient to vs to knowe, that God in déede ſpake with <hi>IONAS,</hi> and that the calling of the Prophet to preache the worde of the Lorde, was done in déede by the will of God. And although there be many curious perſons which thinke thoſe times to be moſt happie, in the which God by ſo many waies ſpake vnto the fathers, and doe affirme that they would more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly beléeue the worde of God, if ſo bée it would pleaſe him to talke with them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that faſhion. Notwithſtanding, if wée well conſider of the matter, nowe that Chriſt is come, and hath publiſhed hys Goſpell throughout the whole worlde, we muſt néedes confeſſe, that the times are much more happie, than they were in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8711:9"/> times paſt. For God hath ſpoken with vs, not by Aungell, not by dreames, or viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but by his owne ſonne our Lord, and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who by his diuine maieſtie excelleth all Aungels. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> it is written.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</note> In theſe laſt dayes God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto vs by his ſonne, whome he hath appointed heyre of all things. And Chriſt himſelfe ſayth:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 13.</note> Bleſſed are the eies which ſée thoſe things that ye ſée. And ſtreyght after he addeth ſaying: many haue deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſée thoſe things that ye ſée, and haue not ſéene them. And the Apoſtle Paule ſayth: Nowe ſaluation is nearer vnto vs than it was then. For ſéeing that the ſonne of God is commended vnto vs by the voyce of God from heauen, ſaying: This is my beloued ſonne, heare him.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 17.</note> He is moſt happye which ſo heareth him by his Goſpell, that by fayth he comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſame, &amp; obeyeth his calling. For whoſoeuer he be that beléeueth not thys ſonne of God, he will not beléeue, though all the Aungels in heauen, all the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, all the Prophetes and fathers
<pb facs="tcp:8711:10"/> ſtoode before him to teſtifie of the worde of God. Wherefore, let vs not neglect the felicitie and happineſſe of our time, but let vs attende and giue eare to the voyce of the ſonne of God, whereby we maye ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne euerlaſting ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Nowe it followeth to ſhewe to what thing the worde of the Lorde called <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS.</hi> Ariſe (ſayth he) goe to that great Citie of <hi>Niniue</hi> and preache in it howe that their wickedneſſe is come vp before me. As concerning the Citie of <hi>Niniue,</hi> and who was the firſt builder of the ſame, we maye reade in the tenth Chapiter of <hi>Geneſis.</hi> This citie was ſo inlarged that in bigneſſe it was comparable to <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> which was fiftéene myles compaſſe, according to the myles of <hi>Germanie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherevpon it followeth in the text: <hi>Niniue</hi> was a great Citie and of thrée dayes iourney.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.</note> And in the ende of this Propheſie,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> it is ſaid, that in that citie there were an .Cxx. thouſande children. Howe great then was the number of men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſeruants, maidens, and ſtraungers? Wherfore <hi>Niniue</hi> was one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8711:10"/> Cities in the whole worlde. And at that time when <hi>IONAS</hi> was ſent vnto it, the mightieſt Monarchie of the whole earth was in the ſame. Moreouer, circumciſed Iewes dwelt not in it, but vncircumciſed Gentiles had their habitation there.</p>
                  <p>When as therefore it pleaſed God to ſende the Prophete <hi>IONAS</hi> vnto it, hée doth plainely declare himſelfe to be no reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecter of perſons, which ſhoulde fauor one nation and abhorre another, and which ſhould be only the God of the Iewes, and not the God of the Gentiles alſo. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God woulde not haue one nation or people, but all men to be ſaued. There is no difference (ſayth <hi>Paule</hi>) betwéene the Iewe &amp; the Gentile, for there is one Lord of all. &amp;c. But this is not ſo to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode as though God ſaueth all the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles without difference, although they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in their impietie, and be not conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the Lorde: but that he deſireth to haue all men ſaued, and reiecteth none that repent &amp; acknowledge the true god. Wherevpon the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth not ſimply, there is one Lorde of all, riche to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:8711:11"/> all. But he addeth: to ſuch as call vpon him. For all ſimplye ſhall not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but all ſuch as call vppon the Lorde. Euery one (ſayeth he) which calleth vpon the name of the Lorde, ſhall be ſaued. But how ſhall they call vppon him in whome they beléeue not? therefore they which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſaued, muſt of neceſſitie heare the worde of God, beléeue the ſame, and call vpon God, through Ieſus Chriſt. For there is ſaluation in no other. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, we maye gather that the <hi>Niniuets</hi> are not ſimply ſaued. But a Prophete is ſent vnto them to declare the worde of God, that they might beléeue and repent.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, when the Lorde ſayth, preache vnto them, bicauſe their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is come vp before me, and ſo forth: he plainly declared what affection he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth towards thoſe that are ſinners. For although he hateth ſinne and iniquitie: yet notwithſtanding, he deſireth to haue all men ſaued, if ſo be they repent. Before the floud came, the Lorde called men to repentance by <hi>Noe.</hi> Before the burning of <hi>Sodome,</hi> the Lorde called the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:8711:11"/> to repentance, by <hi>Loth.</hi> When the deſtruction of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was at hand, the Lorde called the Iewes to repentance by the Prophetes, and afterwarde by Chriſt and the Apoſtles. So in this place before <hi>Niniue</hi> ſhoulde be deſtroyed, the Citizens are called to repentance by <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS.</hi> And bicauſe they repented, they eſcaped puniſhment, as hereafter ſhall be declared.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things therfore are diligentlye to bée conſidered of vs, bicauſe in theſe dayes God hath reuealed himſelfe vnto vs by his worde, and therefore calleth this Realme of Englande to repentaunce. Wherefore, firſt of all let vs conſider and knowe that the wickedneſſe of Englande is aſcended and come before the preſence of God, and that his iuſt wrath and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is at hande for the ſame. For it is not at this time or of late that England hath begonne to ſinne, or to commit abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. But it hath ſinned and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the ſame many yeares, as in Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, in abuſing the name of God, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, in vſurie, yea in all kinde of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:8711:12"/> The which are ſo growne, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and ſo ripe, that they aſcende in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen before the maieſty ſeate of God. Wherfore there is nothing more certaine than that England hath deſerued extreme puniſhment and perdition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A manifeſt token of Gods loue towards vs.</note>Furthermore, let vs vnderſtand and know, that ſéeing the worde of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed and preached ſo fréelye vnto vs, there is ſome hope left vnto vs of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For except the Lorde ſought to ſaue this Realme of Englande, he woulde not haue ſent <hi>IONAS</hi> (I meane the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of his worde) vnto the ſame. Séeing therefore he hath reuealed his will by <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS,</hi> and his whole intent, we haue a manifeſt argument of his clemencie and loue towardes vs. Wherefore, if we will eſcape the puniſhment threatned, we muſt fall to repentance: the vſe wherof hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (God willing) more plainely ſhall be declared. But, and if we be contemners of the worde of God, and impenitent, let vs looke vndoubtedly for deſtruction, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting perdition. Wherevpon our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt ſayth: This is condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8711:12"/> that light came into the worlde, and men loued darkeneſſe more than light.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ And Ionas made him readie to flie vnto Tharſis from the face of the Lorde:<note place="margin">The text</note>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IONAS</hi> flieth to <hi>Tharſis</hi> from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lorde, which ſome interprete to be the ſea, other thinke it to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name of a Citie, which men call now <hi>Tunetum,</hi> ſometime <hi>Carthage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here therefore twoo thinges are to bée conſidered, the one,<note place="margin">Two thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges here to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> is the diſobedience of <hi>IONAS,</hi> and his flight from the preſence of the Lorde. The other, is the cauſe why he fled and was diſobedient to the calling of God.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, let me here demaund a queſtion.<note place="margin">Of flying from the Lorde.</note> What meaneth the Scripture when it ſayth that <hi>IONAS</hi> fled from the preſence of the Lorde? Howe coulde <hi>IONAS</hi> flie from the preſence of God, when as his maieſtie fulfilleth both heauen and earth and all places elſe? Whither ſhall I goe (ſayth the Pſalmiſt) from thy ſpirite, or
<pb facs="tcp:8711:13"/> where ſhall I hyde me from thy preſence: if I climbe vp into heauen, thou art there, &amp; if I go downe to hel, thou art there alſo, and ſo forth. And the Prophete <hi>Amos</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</note> They ſhall not flie awaye: there ſhall not one of them eſcape, nor be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Though they were buried in the hell, my hande ſhall fetch them from thence: though they climbe vp to heauen, yet ſhal I caſt them downe: though they hyde themſelues vppon the toppe of <hi>Carmell,</hi> yet ſhall I ſéeke them out: though they créepe down from my ſight into the déepe of the ſea, I ſhall commaunde the ſerpent euen there to bite them. Let vs therefore note, that if mention be made here of the eternall and omnipotent maieſtie of God, then there is none that can flie from hys hand or preſence. The which thing the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>IONAS</hi> proueth very well.</p>
                  <p>For here he flieth from the hande and preſence of the Lorde, taketh ſhippe, and goeth about to paſſe into a ſtraunge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: yet notwithſtanding, he could not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape from the preſence of the Lorde. God ſawe his flyght, yea, God ſawe his ſecret
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8711:13"/> councell, purpoſe, and intent. And he ſo ſtayeth him wyth his mighty arme in the ſea, that the more he ſéeketh to eſcape, the more ſtraightly he is helde with the hande and power of God, and is caſt into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tréeme peril and daunger which he ſought to auoyde. Wherefore, méere fooliſhe and vaine is their purpoſe, which thinke by their deuiſe and pollicie to eſcape from the power and preſence of God. But where as the ſcripture ſayeth that <hi>IONAS</hi> fled from the preſence of the Lorde, it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he fled out of the lande of Iſraell, in the which, God is ſayde aboue all other nations to dwell. Firſt, bicauſe in that lande was the chiefe place of the Churche of God, and the Arke of the teſtament,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exodus.</hi> 15.</note> by the which it pleaſed God oftentimes to aunſwere. Secondly, bicauſe God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in that lande the publike miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the preaching of his worde, and was wont to reueale himſelfe to the Prophets, and to worke miracles to confirme his promiſes as concerning Chriſt. Laſt of all bicauſe in that lande the ſtocke of Chriſte dwelt, which is the true face and liuelye
<pb facs="tcp:8711:14"/> preſence of God, bicauſe whoſoeuer ſéeth Chriſt, ſéeth the true and euerlaſting God. By this we may learne, that then a man is ſayde to flye from the preſence of God, or to hyde him from his ſight when he flyeth thoſe places, in the which the worde of God is preached, or when hée ſhunneth thoſe men which preache the worde of God. So <hi>Caine</hi> is ſayde to go forth, and to flie from the preſence of God, bicauſe he fled from his father <hi>Adam,</hi> and dwelt farre from him, leaſt he ſhoulde be reprehended of his father by the worde of God. So diſobedient ſeruants and ſonnes flie from the face of God, when they flie from their parents and maiſters, leaſt for their diſobedience they ſhoulde be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the worde of the Lorde and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. So the wicked and vngodlye flie from the face of God, when they deſpiſe the preaching of the word of God, fearing leaſt by the ſame they ſhould be reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from their ſinne &amp; wickedneſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although no man as touching the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie of God, can flie from his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, power, and preſence: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8711:14"/> as touching the externall prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the worde of God, thoſe flie hys preſence, which doe deſpiſe his word, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his ſacraments, continue in diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towardes him, and go forwarde in a wicked lyfe.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall we ſaye then? Can ſuch as flie the preſence of God, eſcape God hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his puniſhment which they ſo feare? No vndoubtedly. For the more they flie the worde and ſacraments of God, the more they fall into his hande, and incurre his wrath, prouoking iuſt vengeance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon themſelues. <hi>Caine</hi> fled from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lorde, but the more he fledde the more hée was tormented with horror of minde. <hi>IONAS</hi> fled from the preſence of the Lorde, but the farther he fled, the more ſubiect he was to perill and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Wherefore, we muſt not flie from God in ſinne, and in the feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but rather we muſt approche vnto God by repentance and inuocation, by the which meanes alone, we eſcape the wrath of God, and the deſerued puniſhment for ſinne. But of this we will ſpeake more
<pb facs="tcp:8711:15"/> plentifully anone.</p>
                  <p>Secondlye, it is demaunded for what purpoſe and intent <hi>IONAS</hi> fledde out of the lande of Iſraell, and woulde not obey the calling of God ſending him to <hi>Niniue.</hi> Of ſundrie men ſundrie and diuers cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are declared and alleaged. Some ſaye that <hi>IONAS</hi> was afearde of the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that might come vnto him at <hi>Niniue</hi> for his ambaſſage ſake. For to preach, that a citie ſhould ſodenly be ouerthrowne and deſtroyed, in the Citie it ſelfe, is inough to ſtirre vp againſt a man all the Citizens &amp; inhabitants of the ſame, and to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be accuſed of ſedition. Other ſome thinke, that <hi>IONAS</hi> feared leaſt that the <hi>Niniuets</hi> which were Ethnickes ſhoulde receyue the worde of God, and repent, and be receyued of the Lord to be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to be reiected. Therefore leaſt his countriemen the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> ſhoulde be reiected, hée rather ſought to flie, than to obey the calling of God. And it maye be that <hi>IONAS</hi> had ſuch cogitations in his mind.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> But <hi>IONAS</hi> himſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth chapter folowing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſeth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8711:15"/> the true and certaine cauſe of his flight. For when God did ſpare the <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets,</hi> and deſtroyed them not, according to the preaching of <hi>IONAS, IONAS</hi> reaſoned with God, and ſayth: O Lorde was not this my ſaying (I pray thée) when I was yet in my countrie? therefore I haſted rather to flie vnto <hi>Tharſis.</hi> By theſe wordes we may plainly gather, that <hi>IONAS</hi> hearing the commaundement of the Lorde, by the which he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to preache the ſubuerſion of the <hi>Niniuets,</hi> thought within himſelfe of the inſpeakable clemency and mercy of God: by the which, God is wont to forgiue thoſe that repent, and ſéeke for the ſame. He feared therefore, leaſt he preaching the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of the <hi>Niniuets,</hi> they in repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhoulde be preſerued, and ſo he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and eſtéemed as a vaine and falſe Prophete. For <hi>IONAS</hi> was not of the common ſort of men, neyther was he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly famous in Iſraell. But he was a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and excellent Prophete, and ſo he was eſtéemed and accounted of, not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes his countriemen, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8711:16"/> among other nations. Which fame he got by this, that according to his propheſie the whole kingdome of <hi>Iſraell</hi> was reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.</note> as it is written in the booke of Kings.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore, <hi>IONAS</hi> feared to impaire his fame and glorie, by preaching that to the <hi>Niniuets</hi> which afterward ſhould not come to paſſe, whereby he myght be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a lyer, the which thing to the vertuous <hi>IONAS</hi> was more grieuous than death.</p>
                  <p>But what? Coulde <hi>IONAS</hi> by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined flight eſcape daungers, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the fame and glorie of his name? No truly: but rather he caſteth hymſelfe into extréeme perill, and doth not only by his diſobedience bring infamy to himſelfe, but alſo putteth his lyfe in venture, and ſuffereth euen the paines of hell, whyle he is conſtreyned thrée dayes to lye in the belly of the Whale, alwayes looking for preſent deſtruction. Here therefore wée maye ſée that the common prouerbe is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes verified: namely, that the wyſe man ſometimes prooueth himſelfe a foole. <hi>IONAS</hi> was the wiſeſt and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holieſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in <hi>Iſraell.</hi> And yet notwithſtanding
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8711:16"/> in this poynt he is ſo ouerwhelmed wyth fooliſhneſſe, that he thinketh by diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſinne to preſerue hys name and fame: not conſidering that by this waye he ſhoulde rather looſe all his goodes, both corporall and ſpirituall, than preſerue and kéepe them from ſhipwracke and hazarde. He knewe no doubt, that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth: that the thing which the vngodly feareth, falleth alway on him. But thys ſaying came not now into hys mynde. For ſo it was wont to come to paſſe, that if God doe ſtaye his hande, then not one Prophet abideth in true obedience.</p>
                  <p>Firſt of all therefore let vs learne by this example of <hi>IONAS</hi> the feare of God. No man ought to truſt to hys wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, holyneſſe, power, or other gyftes, but onely to the clemencie and mercie of God, &amp; in all his actions to call vpon God by Chriſt his ſonne, that he will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to preſerue and kéepe vs in the true obedience of his worde. We maye not by the example of <hi>IONAS</hi> take anye thing raſhly or diſobediently in hande, and ſaye: if God preſerued <hi>IONAS</hi> in his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:17"/> he will alſo preſerue mée: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I alſo will be diſobedient vnto God. This is deteſtable raſhneſſe and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God. For God preſerued <hi>IONAS</hi> not that we ſhould learne to be raſhe, and diſobedient, but bicauſe we ſhould learne to feare God and to obey him, bicauſe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we may fall with <hi>IONAS:</hi> but perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture wée cannot riſe with him againe, ſpecially if we raſhly tempt God. But and if we fall vnaduiſedlye, then the example of <hi>IONAS</hi> teacheth vs to repent, and to truſt to the mercye of god, and ſo we ſhall be deliuered. Furthermore, the example of <hi>IONAS</hi> veryfieth and confirmeth the ſaying of <hi>Salomon,</hi> namelye, that the thing which the vngodly man feareth, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on him. For it is commonly ſéene that men ſéeke to eſcape daunger by impietie and ſinne, as <hi>IONAS</hi> did: who went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to put awaye infamie by diſobeying the will of God. So <hi>Pilate</hi> would auoyde exile and baniſhment from his dominion and office, by ſhedding the innocent bloud of Chriſt. So artificers, merchant men, and other occupiers, goe about to auoyde
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8711:17"/> pouertie and néede, by craft, fraude, and deceyte in bargayning, and ſelling. But that which they ſo greatly feare falleth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them. Let vs therefore abyde in our calling and obedience towards god, ſo ſhal we in déede eſcape all daunger and perill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ And gatte him downe to Ioppa:<note place="margin">The Text.</note> where he founde a ſhip ready to go vnto Tharſis. So he payed his fare and went abourde, that he might go with them vnto Tharſis, from the preſence of the Lorde.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>The diſobedience of <hi>IONAS</hi> is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deſcribed, and nowe his ſecuritie is ſet forth. For after he had determined to flie out of the lande of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> not to <hi>Niniue</hi> wherevnto he was called, but by ſea vnto <hi>Tharſis,</hi> that is to <hi>Aphrica,</hi> in <hi>Carthage,</hi> or as men nowe call it, to <hi>Tunetum,</hi> he taketh his iourney, voyde of all care.</p>
                  <p>He feareth no dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in fléeing, he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not that God is angrye with him for his diſobedience, he thinketh and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe that he is not ſéene, but that
<pb facs="tcp:8711:18"/> he lyeth hidden from the eies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. And therfore he goeth to the ſhip, and payeth his fare that he might ſéeme to be a iuſt and honeſt man. And afterwarde when the tempeſt aroſe, he getteth hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnder the hatches voyde of all care and ſléepeth, thinkinge that this tempeſt peraduenture came eyther by chaunce, or elſe bicauſe of thoſe wicked Idolaters, and vncircumciſed, which were alſo in the ſhippe. In this place of <hi>IONAS</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of humaine ſecuritie after ſinne committed, is deſcribed. For this is the nature of man, namelye, when he hath newly ſinned or committed any kynde of wyckedneſſe, he careleſſelye contemneth the iudgement of god. Hée thinketh then that the wrath of God is not ſo grieuous as it was ſayde to bée, and that hell fire flameth not ſo much as men paynt it out. So <hi>Adam</hi> after the eating of the Apple became careleſſe. He thought himſelfe to be ſufficiently hidden with his aperne of figge leaues. So <hi>Caine</hi> after he had killed his brother, careleſly ſayth, am I the kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of my brother? So <hi>Dauid</hi> when hée
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8711:18"/> had newlye committed adulterie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micide, careleſly he maried the adultereſſe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 11.</note> ſaying: diuers is the chaunce of warre, which ſome while killeth one, ſome while another. So <hi>Iudas</hi> after his treaſon wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked careleſſe for a whyle, not waying the heynous offence that he had committed. So <hi>Peter</hi> when he had denyed Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the damzell,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.</note> ſtoode warmyng hymſelf at the fire voyde of care, as though he had done no euill. To be ſhort, there are infinit examples, by the which we may note that ſinne is of that qualitie and nature, that in the beginning, it hydeth from man the grieuouſneſſe of the wrath of God, and bringeth him to ſecuritie. But thys nature of ſinne, and the qualitie of the ſinner are not only to be knowne, but alſo a remedy for the ſame ought to bée ſought for of vs. Securitie after the ſinne committed is a grieuous diſeaſe, and a great impietie, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it bringeth the contempt of god, the neglecting alſo of the knowledge of his wrath and puniſhmentes, which are the rewardes of ſinne: and kéepeth alſo man in hardneſſe of heart and impenitencye.
<pb facs="tcp:8711:19"/> This trulye is euen to bring man to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tréeme deſtruction. Wherefore, thys diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is expreſſed and ſet forth, not onely that it maye be knowne, but alſo that wée may be ſtirred vppe to ſéeke a remedie for the ſame, bicauſe the neglecting thereof bringeth eternall and euerlaſting death.</p>
                  <p>What ought then to be done, that wée may haue remedye agaynſt this ſecuritie, a diſeaſe of al other moſt pernicious? Firſt we muſt take héede of all ſinne and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: bicauſe (as we ſayde before) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience bringeth with it that foule diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſecuritie. Then if thou be preuented with ſinne, and haſt committed the ſame, ſée thou deferre not the time of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but out of hand with all expedition bewayle thy crime. For god is not woont to puniſh the ſinner immediatly or ſo ſoone as the déede is committed, but deferreth the puniſhment, not that he doth allowe ſinne, but that he looketh for the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the ſinner. If therfore thou repent in time, thou ſhalt eſcape the puniſhment of God.</p>
                  <p>But and if thou perſiſt and go forward
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8711:19"/> in ſinne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> then ſhall thy puniſhment be the greater. If we did iudge of our ſelues we ſhould not be iudged of the Lord. That is, if we after wée had ſinned agaynſt the Lorde, would by and by repent vs of our ſinne we ſhoulde not bée puniſhed at the handes of God. If <hi>IONAS</hi> had repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him of his diſobedience, before he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the ſhippe, then had he not bene brought into ſuch extréeme perill of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke as he was.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ierem.</hi> 18.</note> If that people (ſayeth the Lorde) againſt whome I haue deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a plague, conuert from their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I repent of the plague that I deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bring vppon them. Wherefore leaſt by ſecuritie after ſinne committed, thou be caſt into perpetuall deſtruction, repent without delay, and turne with expedition to the Lorde and mercifull God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ But the Lord hurled a great winde into the ſea,<note place="margin">The text.</note> and there was a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie tempeſt in the ſea, ſo that the ſhippe was in daunger of going in peeces.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IONAS</hi> imagined that the Lorde had
<pb facs="tcp:8711:20"/> forgotten his diſobedience, and was a ſleepe. But as he neyther ſlumbereth nor ſléepeth, which kéepeth Iſraell, that is, the godly and obedient, ſo he ſlepeth not, which puniſheth <hi>Eſau,</hi> that is, all impenitent ſinners. The Lorde therefore ſtirred vp a great tempeſt in the ſea, inſomuch that they which were in the ſhippe diſpayred and were without all hope of life.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, here is to be noted, that tempeſts eyther vppon the ſea, or vppon the lande, come not by chaunce, but by the wyll of God the aucthor of the ſame. For the texte ſayth here, the Lord ſent a mightie winde. Wherefore, we may not thynke that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunters, ſorcerers, or coniurers, can at their will and pleaſure ſtirre vp tempeſts. For except the Lorde permit &amp; ſuffer, not one heare of the heade ſhall ſhake or bée moued. The Lorde therefore is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and not enchaunters.</p>
                  <p>Yet notwithſtanding, ſuch pernicious and wicked perſons were wont to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by publike lawes, bicauſe ſo much as in them lyeth, they go aboute vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly to hurt men, when as notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8711:20"/> they are able to doe nothing without the ſufferance of the Lorde.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Here thou mayeſt ſée (Chriſtian reader) how wicked a thing it is not to obey the calling of God. <hi>IONAS</hi> is diſobedient. And he is not only puniſhed, but alſo thoſe which are wyth him in the ſhippe, are caſt for his ſake into extréeme perill of their liues. Such an example is <hi>Adam,</hi> whych drewe wyth him by his diſobedience, all mankinde into continuall bondage and ſlauery of Sathan. This therefore is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto vs: firſt, that wée may learne to acknowledge the heynous weyght of ſinne, and to beware of the ſame, leaſt that we thereby bring our ſelues, our friendes, and neyghbours into deſtruction. Then that we take héede of the fellowſhip and company of wicked men. Wicked and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient men are blaſphemers, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kardes, fornicators, backbyters, and ſuch lyke, whoſe company and fellowſhip we ought to auoyde, knowing that there is no felicitie in their familiaritie.</p>
                  <p>And let vs ioyne our ſelues with godly and vertuous men, that wyth them our
<pb facs="tcp:8711:21"/> eſtate may be happy and proſperous. For godly and obedient <hi>Paules</hi> ſake all thoſe that were in the ſhippe were preſerued.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Actes.</hi> 26.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider the fooliſhneſſe of diſobedient perſons. <hi>IONAS</hi> thought that he coulde eſcape the puniſhment of God in the ſea, but thereby he caſteth himſelfe into great daunger. For there are no greater exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall daungers than vpon the ſea. As teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.</note> ſaying: They that goe downe to the ſea in ſhippes, and occupie their buſineſſe in great waters, theſe men ſée the workes of the Lorde, and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the déepe. They are caryed vp to heauen and downe agayne to the déepe, their ſoule melteth awaye bicauſe of their trouble. Therefore <hi>IONAS</hi> by that meanes commeth into great daunger, by the which hée thought to eſcape the ſame. This ought diligently to be obſerued and noted of vs, that we may learne to ſhewe vnto God true obedience. For looke what God commaundeth vnto man, the ſame he muſt doe, or elſe periſh, and not eſcape. It was commaunded vnto <hi>IONAS,</hi> that he ſhould preache deſtruction vnto the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8711:21"/> of <hi>Niniue. IONAS</hi> therefore was conſtreyned either to do the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god, or elſe to periſh. Here there is no meane. But this muſt be tranſferred to euery calling of God, and to all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements. God hath commaunded vs not to abuſe his holy name, not to commit adulterie, and ſo forth. Here now we muſt of neceſſitie obey, or periſhe. Neyther can we eſcape deſtruction if we doe not obey, although we fortifie and arme our ſelues neuer ſo much with humaine power. For as <hi>IONAS</hi> by fléeing in the ſea, eſcaped not puniſhment, but caſt himſelfe into the ſame, ſo blaſphemers, adulterers, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and ſuch lyke, in thys are ſubiect to puniſhment, that they thinke and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues to be frée and ſafe from the ſame. Wherefore, there is no other way left to eſcape daunger and puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the way of obedience or repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ Then the Mariners were afrayed,<note place="margin">The Text.</note> and cried euerye man to his God: and the goodes that were in the
<pb facs="tcp:8711:22"/> ſhippe, they caſt into the ſea, to lighten it of them. But IONAS gat him vnder the hatches, where hee layde him downe and ſlumbered. So the maiſter of the ſhippe came to him, and ſayde vnto him: why ſlumbereſt thou? vp, call vpon thy God: if God happilye will thinke vpon vs, that we periſhe not. And they ſayde one to another: come, let vs caſt lots, that we may know, for whoſe cauſe wee are thus trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. And ſo they caſt lottes.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>The Maryners and the reſt in the ſhip were wonderfullye vexed wyth horror of minde, bicauſe of the extréeme daunger in the which they were, without all hope of recouerie. They take in hande notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thrée thinges to deliuer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from perill, if it were poſſible. The firſt is inuocation: the ſeconde is, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lading of the ſhippe, and the thirde is lots. 1 The Mariners did very wel and godly,<note place="margin">Inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> to call vppon God in daunger and perill. For this is a ſpéedye way to eſcape perils,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8711:22"/> or at leaſt to mittigate the ſame.</p>
                  <p>But they being Gentiles and heathen, called not vpon the true God:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Roma.</hi> 1.</note> and therfore they helde this pietie and truth in a lye, as ſayth the Apoſtle <hi>Paule.</hi> They haue not called vpon the true God, by fayth of the ſéede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but euery one (ſayth he) calleth vpon his owne God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon the Mariners exhorted <hi>IONAS</hi> that he woulde call vpon his God. And truely the ſame was done in this Shippe, which was woont to bée done throughout the whole worlde, yea, amongeſt vs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians alſo. For there haue béene ſome, which in daunger called one while vpon our Ladie, another while vpon Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſometime vpon this Saint, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time on that Saint. And if one Saint help not, they runne from Saint to Saint, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to call vpon the true God. This is plaine impietie and heatheniſh Idolatrie. For the Saintes in heauen are ſet foorth vnto vs to declare the clemencie and loue of God, and for examples for vs to imitate their godlineſſe and vertue, and not for vs to call vpon them. But God onely in all
<pb facs="tcp:8711:23"/> perill, trouble, and aduerſitie ought to bée called vpon by his ſonne Chriſt. For there are as well commaundements as promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for the true inuocating vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God alone by fayth in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, we are here admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed what vtilitie and profite there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by affliction and trouble. Men are ſecure and careleſſe when al things are in peace and quiet: but when trouble ary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, they lift vp their heades, they caſt vp their eyes to the heauen, &amp; they call vpon God. Let vs vnderſtand therefore, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it pleaſeth God to ſend a ſwoord, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, or peſtilence, to rayſe vp ſtorme, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, or whatſoeuer for to puniſhe our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, let vs (I ſay) knowe that he doth it, to ſtyrre vs vp to prayer, to inuocation, and repentaunce. By externall tempeſtes, the Lorde ſéeketh oftentymes, to ſtyrre vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall tempeſts in the heart, that we may conſider of the wrath of God towardes ſinners. We ſée here that men in this ſhip were voyde of care before the tempeſt, but the tempeſt and ſtorme béeing vp, they made haſte to prayer, they enquire dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8711:23"/> for the cauſe of the tempeſt, they conſider of the wrath of God, and they ſeke for a remedie. This ſhip therefore is a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of this world, in the which men walk ſecure, before afflictions come. But God ſendeth afflictions, to driue ſecuritie from them, &amp; to cal them to repentance. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs vſe ſwoorde, famine, peſtilence, ſtorme, tempeſt and all kind of plagues, &amp; puniſhments, to our helth, that we know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wrath of God, may obey his will.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The ſeconde thing that theſe Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners take in hande,<note place="margin">The vnla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſhippe.</note> is the vnlading of the ſhip, and the caſting of the goodes into the ſea, that the ſhip might be more light, and eſcape drowning. A ſinguler example of wiſdome ſet forth vnto vs to folow. Theſe Mariners were ſo diſcrete and wiſe, that they rather ſought to loſe all theyr Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundice and goodes which were in the ſhip, than to forſake their lyfe. And it is likely that this ſhip was fraught and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with precious Marchandiſe: and yet notwithſtanding, they are caſt into the ſea, to preſerue lyfe. This example is ſet foorth vnto vs, to admoniſh vs, that as the
<pb facs="tcp:8711:24"/> Mariners to ſaue their corporall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible life, caſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them all their riches: ſo alſo, we ought much more to caſt from vs al things whatſoeuer, to ſaue, preſerue, and kepe our ſpiritual &amp; heauenly life. And if the ſtate and condition of things be ſuch, and if the time ſo ſerue that we may enioy our ſpirituall lyfe, with the preſeruation of our temporall goodes. God is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therewith. But if the caſe ſo ſtande that we cannot kéepe and ſaue our earthly ſubſtaunce vnleſſe we offende and diſobey the will of God: then we muſt rather loſe and forſake our momentany and ruſtie ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches than our heauenly treaſure, which béeing once loſt, can neuer bée recouered and gotten againe. Wherevpon our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt ſayth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> It is better for thée to enter into life, hault, or maymed, rather than thou ſhouldeſt (hauing two hands, or two féete) be caſt into euerlaſting fire. But beleue mée, that the greateſt part of men amonge vs Chriſtians, are not ſo wiſe as theſe heathen Mariners. For, there are (not a few) which had rather not onely that the worde of God, but alſo that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8711:24"/> God himſelfe ſhoulde be forſaken and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed of them, than that they will ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of their gaine to be cut off. In their occupaſion they ſéeke to deceyue: in office they enuy one another, and are am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicious. Theſe, and ſuch like vnlade not their ſhip in perils, but rather fraught the ſame ſo full, that ſhip and all periſheth in the waues of this worlde, before it come to the proſperous hauen of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Wherefore, theſe Mariners ſhall riſe in the laſt daye, and ſhall condemne the greateſt part of Chriſtians, which ſo eſtéeme riches, honors, and the pleaſures of this worlde, that they regarde not true godlyneſſe, or at the leaſt they make ſmall account of the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The thirde thing,<note place="margin">Lottes.</note> is the caſting of lots: the which they take in hand to ſearch out and knowe for whoſe ſake it was that ſo great a tempeſt aroſe. But although it be lawfull ciuillye to vſe lots, in deuiding inheritaunces, as <hi>Ioſua</hi> deuided the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> by lot, or in chooſing of magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates, as the Apoſtles chooſe <hi>Mathie</hi> by lot: this is the ciuille vſe of lots, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8711:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8711:26"/> of the which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 16.</note> The Lots are caſt into the lappe, but the ordering thereof ſtandeth all in the Lord: yet notwithſtanding, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> examples of <hi>IONAS,</hi> of <hi>Achan,</hi> and of <hi>Ionathas,</hi> are not to be imitated and folowed of vs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpeciall calling of God. It is not lawfull for vs by lotte to ſéeke out thoſe thinges that are ſecret and hydden. If any man haue robbed his brother, or ſtollen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye thing in the Citie, and the théefe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, it is not lawfull to trye the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens by lotte, and to apprehende him for the théefe, vpon whome the lot chaunceth. For as it doth not follow that all dreames are true, and that the truth ought to bée ſought out by dreames, bicauſe that <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao</hi> ſawe the truth by dreames, euen ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is not lawfull generally to ſéeke by lot for ſecret théeues, and to bringe them for théeues to the gallowes, vpon whome the lotte chaunceth. This is a temptation of God. What then, doth the example of the caſting of lottes of the Mariners profite vs? Surely in all poynts it ſerueth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for our commoditie. For we ſée that the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8711:26"/> ſinne of <hi>IONAS</hi> which was hidden, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, and vnknowne to all men, to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted and reuealed not naturallye, but miraculouſlye by lotte. Let vs therefore know and well aſſure our ſelues, that no ſinne, no wickedneſſe how ſecret ſoeuer it be, can be hydde from the preſence of the Lorde. Men commonlye ſinne in ſecrete, and thereby they hope to eſcape vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, bicauſe their ſinne is not manifeſt. But although ſinne bée vnknowne and hidden from the eyes of men: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it is not hydde from the ſight of God, who reuealeth and maketh them knowen oftentimes to all the worlde, by extraordinarie meanes. Wherefore, the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, whither ſhall I go then from thy ſpirite, or where ſhall I hide mée from thy preſence. &amp;c. Alſo the wyſe man ſayth:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astes.</hi> 10.</note> Wiſhe the king no euill in thy thought, and ſpeake no hurt of the riche in thy priuie chamber: for a byrde of the ayre ſhall bewray thy voyce, and with hir fethers ſhall ſhe bewraye thy wordes. Beware therefore that thou ſinne not in ſecrete vppon hope to eſcape vnpuniſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:27"/> but abſtayne from all ſinne, as well ſecret as open and manifeſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">The Text.</note>¶And the lot fell vpon IONAS. Then ſayde they vnto him: tell vs for whoſe cauſe we are thus troubled: what is thine occupation? whence commeſt thou, and whither goeſt thou? what Countrieman arte thou, and of what nation? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them. I am an Hebrue, and I feare the Lorde God of Heauen, which made both the ſea and drie lande. Then were the men excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly afrayde, and ſaid vnto him: why diddeſt thou ſo? (for they knewe that he was fledde from the preſence of the Lorde, bicauſe hee had tolde them) and ſayde more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer vnto him, what ſhall we doe vnto thee, that the ſea maye ceaſe from troublinge vs: For the ſea wrought, and was troublous. Hee aunſwered them: take me and caſt me into the ſea, ſo ſhall it let you be in reſt: for I wotte it is for my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8711:27"/> ſake that this greate tempeſt is come vppon you. Neuertheleſſe, the men aſſayed with rowyng to bring the ſhippe to lande, but it woulde not bee: bicauſe the ſea wrought ſo ſore, and was ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous againſt them. Wherefore they cryed vnto the Lorde, and ſayde: O Lorde, let vs not periſh for this mans death, neyther lay thou innocent bloude vnto our charge: for thou, O Lorde, haſt done euen as thy pleaſure was. So they tooke IONAS, and caſt him into the ſea, and the ſea left ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. And the men feared the Lorde exceedingly, doing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and making vowes vnto the Lorde.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IONAS</hi> is founde out by lot. Hitherto hath bene deſcribed the ſecure and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient fléeing and ſtarting aſide of <hi>IONAS.</hi> Nowe it is declared that he is brought to the acknowledging of his fault, and that his ſecuritie is altered and chaunged into
<pb facs="tcp:8711:28"/> extréeme tremblinge feare, and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For as <hi>Peter</hi> at the thirde tyme of the crowing of the Cocke, remembred the wordes of Chriſt, and by and by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged his ſinne, and wept bitterly: euen ſo <hi>IONAS,</hi> beinge bewrayed by lotte, ſtreightway vnderſtoode that the tempeſt aroſe for his ſake, and felt the greatneſſe of his ſinne. Wherefore, by his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde he confeſſeth hys ſinne, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the deſerued puniſhment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, namely, that he muſt bée caſt into the ſea. Take me (ſayth hée) and caſt me into the ſea, ſo ſhall it let you be at reſt.</p>
                  <p>Here wée haue in <hi>IONAS</hi> thoſe thrée parts of repentance, which the hypocrites (the Papiſts I meane) doe teach, to be the ſatiſfactions for ſinne. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, he is ſo impotent, weake, and vnable to ſatiſfie for his ſinne, that vnleſſe he had béene preſerued by the mercye of God, he had periſhed euerlaſtinglye. For firſt he had contrition, bicauſe he beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his ſinne, and felt the wrath of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt him for the ſame. Secondlye, hée
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8711:28"/> confeſſed his ſinne, not in the eare of a Prieſt, but publikely to all thoſe that were in the ſhippe. Laſt of all, he ſatiſfied for the ſinne that he had committed (ſay the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes) when he had commaunded the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners to caſt him into the ſea. So <hi>Iudas</hi> had theſe thrée Papiſticall parts of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. He had contrition, bicauſe he was ſory that he had betrayed Chriſt. Hée had confeſſion, bicauſe he confeſſed his trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous fault before the hye Prieſts, ſaying, I haue ſinned in betrayinge the innocent bloude. He had alſo ſatiſfaction, for deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately he hanged himſelfe. I praye God giue theſe enimes of his ſonne Chriſt, if it be his wyll, a more righteous and iuſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction, than this hypocriticall ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the reaſon why <hi>IONAS</hi> obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned remiſſion of his ſinne, and not <hi>Iudas,</hi> when as both of them had theſe thrée parts of repentance, ſhall be hereafter God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhewed: Now let vs ſée what things are to bée gathered and obſerued in this place.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, know we that <hi>IONAS</hi> was a Prophete, accepted and beloued of the
<pb facs="tcp:8711:29"/> Lorde. And yet notwithſtanding, when he tooke not his iorney to <hi>Niniue</hi> at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Lorde, he was caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to grieuous puniſhement, when as his ſinne might ſéeme to be not ſo horrible and gréeuous. For <hi>IONAS</hi> had neyther committed homicide, nor adultery, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye refuſed to preache to wicked men. Is this ſo great an offence? Were there not many in the lande of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> which had committed moſt cruell déedes? and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, led a ſecure &amp; quiet lyfe. Were not the Mariners themſelues which were Ethnickes, and heathen, more heynous, and horrible offenders than <hi>IONAS?</hi> For they were Idolators. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, theſe eſcape daunger, onely <hi>IONAS</hi> is caſt into the ſea, and is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of the Whale, when as in déede the other deſerued to be ſwallowed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured both of ſea, fiſhe, and lande. But this is the ſame which <hi>Peter</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 4.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Iudgement beginneth at the houſe of God,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>EZech.</hi> 9.</note> that is, when God goeth aboute to puniſhe, he beginneth firſt with his ſaints. Alſo the Lorde himſelfe by the mouth of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8711:29"/> the Prophete <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſayeth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iere.</hi> 25.</note> In the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie where my name is called vpon, will I begin to puniſh. So <hi>Malchus</hi> the ſeruant of the hie Prieſt, offended more than did <hi>Peter:</hi> and yet notwithſtanding, <hi>Peter</hi> is reprehended, and <hi>Malchus</hi> hath his eare reſtored. The almightye God doth as the mayſter of a houſholde or family is woont to doe, which firſt of all reformeth hys owne houſholde. Wherefore, wée muſt learne and knowe thys, that when we are afflicted, and ſée in the meane ſeaſon wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men to eſcape vnpuniſhed, that the almightie doth it, to ſignifie vnto vs, that we are of his familie and houſholde, and that therefore he beginneth firſt to puniſhe vs. Wherefore, let vs paciently receyue his puniſhment, and repent vs of oure ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, although the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners went about to bring the ſhippe vnto land, leaſt they ſhould caſt him into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea, whom they iudged innocent: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more they ſtriued agaynſt the ſtreame, the greater was the tempeſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the vnlading of the ſhip help them
<pb facs="tcp:8711:30"/> any thing at all.</p>
                  <p>By this example we are taught that the daungers which are ſent of God, are not auoyded by mans pollicie and witte, but onely by obedience, which is due to God. It was humane pollicie to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade and lighten the ſhip: it was humane pollicie to bring the ſhip to ſhore: but thoſe deuiſes profited nothing. Onely obedience would haue profited. For God layde the puniſhment vpon <hi>IONAS,</hi> and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Mariners to be executours of the ſame. This office, this obedience, was fulfilled of the Mariners. Wherfore they ſought not to auoyde the perill and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, before they left theyr owne deuiſes, and obeyed the councell and motion of god in caſting <hi>IONAS</hi> into the Sea. The which councell, and will of God was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed as well by lot as by the confeſſion of <hi>IONAS</hi> himſelfe. This example in theſe difficult and daungerous tymes is to be conſidered, ſpeciallye of Magiſtrates, parents, and Maiſters of houſholdes. For God hath euen nowe begonne to puniſhe vs, and to afflict vs for our ſinnes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealeth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8711:30"/> his wrath by diuers ſtormie, and boyſterous tempeſtes. For at this preſent he afflicteth vs with warre, with penurie, with peſtilence, with ciuill contention, and greater plagues no doubt than theſe hang ouer our heades, and are at hande. And what doe we to auoyde, or eſchew this iuſt vengeance of God? Surely, according to our accuſtomed and naturall woont, wée followe our owne deuices, we truſt vnto them, we make fleſhe our arme. Agaynſt the forreyne enimie, we fortifie and arme our ſelues. But what doth that profite vs againſt the wrath of God? To auoyde the plague or peſtilence (ſo called) we take pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiues, &amp; diuers medicines, but what can they preuayle agaynſt the wrath of God? (Yet notwithſtanding, I ſay not that the vſe of ſuch ordinarie meanes are to be forſaken.) But if we will preuayle, and haue good ſucceſſe, we muſt cloth our ſelues with repentaunce, wée muſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our ſelues with obedience, and wée muſt arme our ſelues with fayth. God commaundeth the Magiſtrate to puniſhe the fault, and offence of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:31"/> euen as he required the Mariners to caſt <hi>IONAS</hi> into the ſea. Except there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this commaundement be obeyed in puniſhing the enimies of God (I meane the Papiſtes) the blaſphemer, the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karde, the fornicator, the vſurer, and ſuch lyke, the wrath, and puniſhment of God cannot haue an ende. The wrath of God fell vpon the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> for whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.</note> but after that <hi>Phinees</hi> began to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe the ſame, the wrath of God was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudges.</hi> 7.</note> The lyke example we haue of <hi>Achan,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
                  <p>But we muſt take an enſample of theſe Mariners, and conſider with howe great feare of God Magiſtrates ought to puniſh the wicked. For they tooke not in hande to caſt <hi>IONAS</hi> into the ſea, before they had made theyr prayers vnto God, ſaying: we beſéech thée, O Lorde, ſuffer vs not to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. This example all Magiſtrates ought to followe in puniſhing malefactors, and wicked offendors. For to puniſh wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to put the malefactors to death, is a worke onely pertayning to the diuine power of God. For in the lawe it is ſayde
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8711:31"/> thou ſhalt not kill. This lawe is naturall, pertayning generally to all men. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon before the floud, when as Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were not ordeyned, it was not lawfull for any man, though he were a murtherer to be put to death. <hi>Caine,</hi> and (as ſome thinke) <hi>Lamech,</hi> were murtherers, yet they were not put to death.</p>
                  <p>But after the floud the office of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate was ordeyned, to the which: God gaue power and authoritie to put male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors to death, according to lawe. All Magiſtrates therefore, ought to execute their office with the feare of god, leaſt they puniſhe the innocent for the offender.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT the LORDE prepared a great Fiſhe to ſwallowe vppe IONAS.<note place="margin">The text.</note>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THis ſentence comprehendeth few wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, and marke them well, they bring vnto vs great comfort,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:32"/> and conſolation in al aduerſities and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. For wheras the Text ſayth, not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, that <hi>IONAS</hi> was caſt into the ſea, and deuoured of the fiſh, but that the Lord prepared a fiſhe, which ſwalowed vp <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS:</hi> it manifeſtlye declareth, that the clemencie and prouidence of the Lorde is ſo great, in preſeruing his people, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending his Church, that he will ſuffer no hurt, or harme to happen vnto them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he haue appoynted, and prouided a meane and waye before, by the which hée may preſerue and deliuer them: the which thing both the examples and promiſes of ſcripture doe teſtifie. Among examples, let this which we haue here of <hi>IONAS,</hi> be the firſt. For although the Lorde was angrye with <hi>IONAS</hi> for his diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: yet notwithſtanding, bicauſe he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth him, not onely for a member of his Church, but alſo for a Prophete be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of him, he prepareth for him a lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, or gueſt Chamber in the ſea, before he was caſt into the ſame. For he woulde neuer haue ſuffered the Mariners to caſt <hi>IONAS</hi> into the ſea, vnleſſe he had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéene,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8711:32"/> and prouided firſt a meane, by the which hée might preſerue him in the ſea, and deliuer him againe. Another example we haue in the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed many yeares, vnder the cruell ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie of <hi>Pharao</hi> in <hi>Aegypt:</hi> and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, they were the people or Church of God. But vnleſſe God had foreſene and prouided a way, by the which he might deliuer them, from ſo cruell ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, he would neuer haue ſuffred them to haue come into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and to haue béene there afflicted. For that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided ſuch a meane before his people went into <hi>Aegypt</hi> and were there afflicted, it is euident by the fiftene of <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gene.</hi> 15.</note> where it is fayde vnto <hi>Abraham.</hi> Thy ſéede ſhall be a ſtraunger in a lande that appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not vnto them. And ſhall ſerue them, and they ſhall intreate them euill foure hundred yeares. But afterward they ſhall come out with great ſubſtaunce. Here we may ſée that God had appoynted a meane to deliuer them out of affliction before they were afflicted.</p>
                  <p>An other example we haue in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens
<pb facs="tcp:8711:33"/> of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> For it was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that within a hundred yeares or there aboutes after the death of <hi>Ezechias, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> ſhould be deſtroyed of the <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> &amp; the Citizens caried into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity. But before this thing came to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord prepared <hi>Cyrus</hi> to be their deliuerer, of whom <hi>Eſay</hi> prophecied,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 44. <hi>and</hi> .45.</note> the ſaid <hi>Cyrus</hi> being yet vnborne, and promiſed deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to his church, before affliction came.</p>
                  <p>For of ſo great priſe is the Church or Congregation of the Lorde vnto him, that he winketh not at the aduerſaries, but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth them in the ende, and deliuereth his Church from all trouble and vexation. And therefore alſo the Prophete <hi>Ieremie</hi> prophecied the certaine time of the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the people out of <hi>Babilon,</hi> ſaying that they ſhoulde be ſet frée the ſeuenth hundreth yeare.</p>
                  <p>But the ſpeciall example is of Chriſt Ieſus the ſonne of God, for he ſuffered the moſt ſhamefull death of the Croſſe. But before he tooke vpon him our humaine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and was borne of the virgin, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets preached of his death, reſurrection,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8711:33"/> and kingdome. As wée maye reade in the thrée and fiftie Chapter of <hi>Eſay,</hi> and in many other places.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> For God ſo loued his onely begotten ſonne, that he woulde not haue ſuffered the Iewes ſo cruelly to haue put him to death, vnleſſe he had before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted and determined how to ſaue and deliuer him.</p>
                  <p>But ſome man will ſay: I graunt in déede that this hapned to Chriſt the ſonne of God, to <hi>IONAS</hi> likewiſe, and to other Prophetes, and holy men. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                     </label> But I am ſo abiect, baſe, and contemned, that he hath no care, reſpect, or regard vnto me. Again, my ſinnes and offences are ſo heynous, that God careth not what euill happeneth vnto mée, his wrath is ſo kindled againſt me. We are truely contemned,<note place="margin">Reſpond.</note> if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our corporall eſtate, and our ſinnes no doubt doe prouoke the wrath of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. But he which reiecteth ſinners for their ſinne, he alſo receyueth ſinners through repentaunce. And although as touching our corporall eſtate, we are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and ſubiect to death: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, if we be of the Church of Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:34"/> then are we in the ſight of God an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent treaſure. Wherefore, we muſt ſéeke by all meanes to come to repentance, and to be members of the Church of Chriſt, The which thing we ſhall bring to paſſe, when we acknowledging our ſinnes, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Ieſus Chriſt, by a true fayth, and walke by this fayth, in inuocation and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon God, and in good workes, which God hath commaunded. In ſo doing, all the promiſes of the care and prouidence of God mentioned in holy ſcripture pertaine vnto vs.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>EZech.</hi> 33.</note> I liue ſayth the Lorde, and will not the death of a ſinner, but rather that hée turne from his wickedneſſe, and liue. The Lorde is nigh vnto all thoſe that are of a contrite heart,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.</note> and an humble ſpirite. Moreouer,<note place="margin">Ier. <hi>3.</hi> lamen</note> the Lorde is nigh vnto all thoſe that call vpon him. And our ſauiour Chriſt ſayth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> All the heares of your heade are numbred.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">The text.</note>¶And IONAS was in the belly of the Whale, three daies, and three nights.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>This is that myracle which the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8711:34"/> and faithfull do woonder at, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the vngodly and infidels, doe ſcoffe and ieſt. Neyther is their any doubt but that <hi>Lucian</hi> tooke occaſion by this place to write and indyte his booke of true Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the ende he might therby ſet forth the doctrine and miracles of holy ſcripture to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world, to be derided, and ieſted at. But that ſcoffing <hi>Lucian,</hi> and wicked Ethnicke, receyued a iuſt rewarde of hys impietie. But let vs vnderſtande, and knowe, that although this myracle of <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> (being thrée dayes, and thrée nights in the belly of the Whale) ſéemeth to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine reaſon, not onely ridiculous, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo impoſſible: yet notwithſtanding, wée ought in no wiſe to doubt, as concerning the veritie and truth of this matter. For firſt of all, this hyſtorie of <hi>IONAS,</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the Canonicall bookes of holye ſcripture, neyther ought we to doubt in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poynt of the authoritie of the ſame, for as yet it was neuer vncertaine. Looke howe great therefore the certaintie and truth of the whole ſumme of ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is, ſo great alſo is the certaintie and
<pb facs="tcp:8711:35"/> truth of this myracle.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, Chriſt himſelfe the ſonne of God our Lorde, commendeth vnto vs this myracle by name ſaying: As <hi>IONAS</hi> was in the Whales belly thrée dayes, and thrée nightes, ſo muſt the ſonne of man be. &amp;c. Euen as therefore the aucthoritie of Chriſt was confirmed by heauenly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, and myracles, as by clenſing the Lepers, by reſtoring the Lame to lymme, by rayſing the deade, and ſuch like: euen ſo alſo the truth of this myracle of <hi>IONAS</hi> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the ſame myracles. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although the heathniſh Ethnicks de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride our credulitie, and beliefe: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, there is nothing more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ſure, and firme, than theſe myracles. Our dayly and common myracles, doe confirme ſomewhat the truth of this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of <hi>IONAS.</hi> As for example. Doth not the infant,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Embryon</hi> is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfit ſhape of the child being in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe.</note> or rather that which the <hi>Greekes</hi> call <hi>Embryon,</hi> lye many wéekes aliue in the mothers wombe: and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, is neyther choked nor kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but rather, receyueth more perfite ſtrength? Theſe and ſuch like are dayly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8711:35"/> ſéene: and yet notwithſtanding, bicauſe they are common, they are rather counted naturall, than myraculous. But in déede they are no leſſe myracles than this which concerneth <hi>IONAS.</hi> Wherfore the ſame God which preſerueth and quickneth, by his omnipotent power the vnperfit childe, in the mothers wombe, preſerued alſo <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> in the Whales belly.</p>
                  <p>But this myracle hath his vſe. Firſt, as God exerciſed and tryed the fayth of <hi>IONAS,</hi> being as yet in the belly of the Whale, ſo he confirmed the ſame, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Whale to caſt him a lande ſafe and ſounde. Furthermore, it certefieth vs that in all our affliction we ſhall receyue the helpe of God, if we call vpon God, as <hi>IONAS</hi> did, as hereafter foloweth.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all, this myracle prefigured the death, buriall, and reſurrection of Chriſt, as Chriſt himſelfe expoundeth the ſame. Wherefore by this myracle we are admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as well of the clemency of God in aduerſitie, as of the death, and the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt, that we alſo might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a hope of deliueraunce, and be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb facs="tcp:8711:36"/> and ſurelye perſwaded of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">The text.</note>¶ And IONAS prayed vnto the Lord his God, out of the fiſhes bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and ſayde: In my trouble I called vnto the Lord, and he heard me, out of the bellie of hell I cried and thou heardeſt my voice.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>Here followeth the Pſalme which <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> made to giue thankes vnto God for his benifits. But we muſt not thinke that he had ſo much leyſure, that hée myght walke vp and downe in the Whales belly ſecurely, and ſing this Pſalme, to paſſe away the time: for he was ouerwhelmed with infinite dolors and griefes of death, and hell, hauing no hope almoſt of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce.</p>
                  <p>Therefore he prayed vnto the Lorde in the Whales bellye, both with a ſorowfull minde, and wyth an vndoubted fayth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. But after he was deliuered, and had eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped daunger, hée made this Pſalme, by the whiche hée did not onelye declare the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8711:36"/> thankfulneſſe of hys minde towards god, but alſo commended this myracle to his poſteritie, that all men being in daunger, by his example ſhould call vpon God, and looke for vndoubted helpe at his hande.</p>
                  <p>It was a common cuſtome among the auncient fathers in olde time to commit the diuine miracles into publik verſes and pſalmes, which is an acceptable kynde of ſeruice of God, as teſtifieth the Pſalmiſt, I wil praiſe the name of God with a ſong, and will magnifie him, and it ſhall pleaſe God more than a Bullock that hath horns and hoofes. For firſt of all by this worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God, his goodneſſe, clemency, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and omnipotencie is ſet forth.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, men are ſtirred vppe to fayth and inuocation of God in all aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. Theſe are the holy and acceptable thinges which pleaſe God, and by the which wée ought to declare a thankefull minde for thoſe benifites that wée haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued. And if any man require examples of this matter, we haue <hi>Moſes, Debora, Anna</hi> the mother of <hi>Samuell, Dauid, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias, Zacharias</hi> the father of <hi>Iohn</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8711:37"/> the Baptiſt, <hi>Symeon,</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt for examples. Wherefore it is our partes and duties to knowe, and learne ſuch Pſalmes, and by theſe wée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admoniſhed of the diuine miracles, maye conceyue a firme and vndoubted hope in aduerſitie, and may ſtirre vp the holy ghoſt, by the which we are made apt to call vppon God, and ſo wée ſhall be in déede deliuered in aduerſitie. For euerye man which calleth vpon the name of God ſhall be ſaued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">This Pſalme conſiſteth of ſeauen verſes.</note>But to returne to our Pſalme, which <hi>IONAS</hi> made, and committed to the Church to be ſong, wée muſt know that it comprehendeth ſeauen verſes. The firſt verſe is: I cryed in my trouble vnto the Lorde, and he hearde mée. This verſe comprehendeth in it ſelfe the argument and ſumme of the whole Pſalme, namely, that <hi>IONAS</hi> was ouerwhelmed with great ſorrowes and griefe of the mynde. But when he called vppon the Lorde by fayth, hée was wonderfully and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly deliuered.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt of all therefore, when he turneth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8711:37"/> himſelfe aright, vnto the Lord, not to any of the Patriarches which were deade, he teacheth vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wée ought not in our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, to turne vs eyther by vowes or pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto deade Saincts, but onely to God the father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and that in the name of Chriſt, and for Chriſt his ſake, ſéeing that we haue a manifeſt promiſe:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.</note> Whatſoeuer ye aſke of the father in my name, he will giue it you.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Furthermore, it teacheth vs, what time is moſt apt to offer our prayers and ſupplications vnto God. Ignoraunt and vnlearned men iudge, and eſtéeme, that that time is fitte and méete to praye vnto God, when eyther they riſe in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or go to bedde at night, or elſe when they leade a happie and proſperous lyfe: and truly we ought not to pretermit pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at theſe times and ſeaſons. But when as great and grieuous afflictions do ariſe, and daungerous perilles approche, men thinke then that it is hye time, and more fitte to blaſpheme, to curſe, and to rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt God and men, than to praye vnto God. But the Prophet when he ſayth, in
<pb facs="tcp:8711:38"/> my trouble I cryed vnto the Lorde, and from the bellie of hell I cried, he plainelye declareth that then, the time is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to praye vnto God, when great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils are at hand, and we compaſſed round about with preſent death, as teſtifieth the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.</note> ſaying: The Lorde is nigh vnto them that are of a broken hart, and he will ſaue ſuch as are of an humble ſpirit.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> And agayne: Call vpon me in the daye of trouble, and I will deliuer thée, and thou ſhalt glorifie me. Alſo it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: I am with him in trouble, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him and glorifie him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, the Prophete teacheth vs by his owne example in all our trouble, to looke for certaine helpe and deliuerance, if we repent and cal vpon God by true faith. For the Prophete fell into this daunger, not for his owne righteouſneſſe &amp; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods calling, but for vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and diſobedience, by the which hée fled the calling of God: yet neuertheleſſe when in the middeſt of daungers hée ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged his ſinne, and conuerted him ſelfe by fayth and prayer vnto the Lorde,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8711:38"/> he was hearde, ſaued, and miraculouſlye deliuered. Externall ſaluation, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance is not alwaies wont to happen to euery one in extréeme perils and daunger. Yet notwithſtanding it is moſt certaine and ſure, that if a ſinner euen in the midſt of his trouble and aduerſitie, repent and conuert vnto the Lorde, he ſhall alwayes obtayne true, and eternall ſaluation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſhoulde periſhe with corporall death. Wherevpon the Pſalmiſt ſayth, Approche vnto the Lorde, and be lightned, and ye ſhall not be aſhamed. This poore man <hi>IONAS</hi> cried, and the Lorde heard him. And Chriſt himſelfe ſayth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 11.</note> I am the reſurrection and the lyfe, he that beléeueth in me though he were deade, yet ſhall he liue. Wherefore let not our ſinnes diſmay or diſcourage vs from calling vppon God in our trouble and aduerſitie, but rather let them be a meane to ſtirre vs vp to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that we may call vpon God by fayth, and looke certainly at his hands for the promiſed ſaluation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ Thou haddeſt caſt me down in the<note place="margin">The text.</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8711:39"/> middeſt of the ſea, and the floude compaſſed me about: yea, all thy waues and rowles of water went o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me. I thought that I had bene caſt awaye out of thy ſight. But I will yet agayne looke towarde thy holy temple. The waters compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mee, euen to the verie ſoule: the deepe laye about mee, and the weedes were wrapt about my head. I went downe to the bottome of the hilles, and was barred in wyth earth for euer.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>In the firſt verſe of this Pſalme, the whole ſtate, and ſumme of the Pſalme is conteined, as we haue ſhewed before. And now the other ſeauen verſes followe: in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which, that which was briefly compriſed in the firſt verſe, is plentifully expounded.</p>
                  <p>And firſt of all the Prophet rehearſeth and expoundeth the tribulations, afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſorrowes which he ſuffered, the which no man can ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vnderſtand, vnles he himſelf at ſome time féele in dede the lyke. Thou hadſt caſt me (ſayth hée)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8711:39"/> down in the middeſt of the ſea. We know that the Prophete was caſte of the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners into the ſea, and receyued of the Whale. Beholde therfore and ſée how co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſlye he doth expounde and dilate thys thing. Thou haſt caſt me not ſimply in the ſea, but in the déepe of the ſea, in the hart of the ſea, in the middeſt of the ſea, that the water might compaſſe me about on euery ſide, yea, that all thy waues and rowles of water might go ouer me. For I did not only ſwimme vpon the ſuperficiall part of the ſea, but alſo when I was receyued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Whales bellie, the waters did ſo compaſſe me, that they entred euen into my ſoule, that is, I was euen ready to bée choked. For I was in the déepe of the ſea, and when the heade of the Whale, in the which I laye, was wrapped about with wéedes and ſedge, I ſéemed alſo to be tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled and tyed in the ſame, inſomuch that I looked for no waye to eſcape. Neyther was I caried ſimplye by the ſea ſhore, but of neceſſitie I was conſtreyned to beare the Whale companie euen to the ſtéepe and déepe valleyes of the mountaynes in
<pb facs="tcp:8711:40"/> the ſea, where I thought my ſelfe to bée barred in for euer. To be ſhort, bicauſe I was in the Whales bellie, I was ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the ſea, that I had no hope to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered. In ſo great therefore, and horrible daunger, I was ſo affected and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that I thought my ſelfe as touching my corporall health and lyfe, to be reiected and caſt out of Gods fauour, for I neuer looked to eſcape alyue out of the Whales bellie, and to ſée and viſite the holy temple at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> &amp; to be conuerſant among men agayne. Thus we haue the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſticall expoſition of theſe verſes, in the which the Prophete ſheweth the daunger that he was in, and the affection of his minde. And now let vs ſée what thinges ought ſpecially in theſe wordes to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and obſerued.</p>
                  <p>Firſt of all the Prophete ſpeaketh vnto God, and affirmeth that he was caſt by him into the ſea. But it is manifeſt that the Mariners caſt him into the ſea. And yet notwithſtanding we ſée that <hi>IONAS</hi> pretermitting the Mariners ſayth vnto God: Thou haddeſt caſt me downe. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8711:40"/> doth he ſay, the rowles and waues of the ſea, but he ſayth, thy waues, and thy rowles went ouer mée. By the which wordes the Prophete teacheth vs, that in aduerſitie &amp; trouble, we ought not to haue reſpect to the inſtrumentall cauſes of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, but rather to looke &amp; haue regarde vnto God the author of the ſame. For we are ſo corrupt and affected by nature, that we attribute, and referre the cauſes of our afflictions, eyther to men, or to Sathan. And as it is commonly ſayd of the Beare, that when ſhée is hurt, ſhée reuengeth hir ſelfe on that which is next vnto hir: euen ſo man being offended, inueyeth agaynſt the next or ſeconde cauſe, by which hée ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bée offended and hurte. But if wée conſider well, wée ſhall finde it our parts in all aduerſitie and trouble, to lifte vp our eyes vnto heauen to God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the true and firſt cauſe of aduerſitie, and the author thereof. For neyther Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than nor man, nor any other creature can hurt vs, no they can not moue one heare of our heade, vnleſſe before, power be giuen &amp; graunted of God from aboue. One heare
<pb facs="tcp:8711:41"/> (ſayth our ſauiour Chriſt) falleth not to the grounde without the will of your heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> And the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his lamentations, ſayth: What is he which ſayde that neyther good nor euill ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede out of the mouth of the moſt higheſt? The which thing, when good and godlye men conſidered, they turned not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to contumelious ſayinges, to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous othes, to execrable and bitter curſinges, in aduerſitie and affliction, as though men or anye other creatures, had bene the authors of the ſame: But they rather turned themſelues by godly obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and prayer, vnto God, which is the ſpeciall author of affliction and trouble.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</note>For althoughe wée our ſelues are the principall cauſe of al our afflictions by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our ſinne: yet notwithſtanding, we ſpeake not of the deſeruing cauſe of afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but of the inferring and bringinge cauſe of afflictions, the which is God, the worker and giuer of all thinges,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> without whoſe will and prouidence the little Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe falleth not to the grounde.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</note> So <hi>Iobe</hi> ſayde: The Lord giueth and the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8711:41"/> awaye, when the <hi>Chaldees</hi> tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye his ſhéepe and oxen, when the fire burned his corne, and when the winde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrewe the houſe in the which his ſonnes and daughters were banquetting.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Daniell</hi> ſayeth, that the Lorde caſt the Iewes out of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> into all landes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</note> when as notwithſtandinge the <hi>Babilonians</hi> did it. So <hi>IONAS</hi> in this place affirmeth that the Lorde caſt him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſea, when (as it appeareth by the text) the Mariners did it. But we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in aduerſitie ſay: The Lord gaue, and the théeues haue taken: The Lorde gaue, and the fire conſumed: The Lorde gaue, and the ſea hath drowned: contrary to the examples of <hi>Iob, Daniell,</hi> and <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS,</hi> who had not cauſe vnto the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall cauſe, but vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principall cauſe.</p>
                  <p>Let vs learne therfore by this example, in all our trouble, to lyft vp our eyes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde God of heauen onely, and to impute the cauſe of all our trouble vnto him, that we thereby knowing the will of God, may conceyue pacience, and be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to repentaunce and inuocation, by
<pb facs="tcp:8711:42"/> the which we maye obteyne the true ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, the which we cannot obteyne, if we referre the cauſe of our aduerſitie to creatures (which are but the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall cauſe) and ſo fall to banning and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we ſée, that <hi>IONAS</hi> being in the Whales bellie, trembled wyth great horror and feare of death. When the waters (ſayth he) compaſſed me, euen to the very ſoule. Whereby he declareth that with a fearefull minde, he looked eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment for preſent death.</p>
                  <p>The Legendes of Saynctes doe declare vnto vs, that they ſuffered death, voyde almoſt of all payne, and that they went to their death with no leſſe courage and ioye, than if a Mayde ſhoulde prepare hir ſelfe to the daunce. And trulye by the goodneſſe of God we haue ſéene by experience, that one man hath gone to his death with a more ſtoute and valiaunt minde than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For we may not thinke that they are in happye ſtate which are withdrawne by great feare of death, for God doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times exerciſe his Saints with this feare,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8711:42"/> that they maye haue a perfite féeling and vnderſtandinge of the imbecilicie and weakeneſſe of their fleſh, and may be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp thereby to be the more feruent in prayer to God. Who was more ſtronge, more holye, and more mightie than the ſonne of God? And yet notwithſtanding, when he ſhould ſuffer death he was vexed with ſo great feare that hée trembled, and bled a bloudie ſweate. What ſhall we ſaye then? Did he not knowe that by this death he ſhoulde redéeme mankinde, and enter into the glorie of his father? Yes vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly he knew it. What did he feare then? He feared to declare himſelfe to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite man, and by this feare, to ſatiſfie for man, and to haue the victory ouer the feare of death, that if we at any time ſhoulde be troubled with feare, ſhoulde not diſpaire, but haue a certayne and ſure hope, and call vpon God for deliueraunce.</p>
                  <p>For he doth not reiect vs for our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becilitie, but the more weake and fearefull wée are, the more care hée hath ouer vs. Was not <hi>Dauid</hi> a valiant man, a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a worthie, and a holy Prophete? And
<pb facs="tcp:8711:43"/> yet notwithſtanding, when hée thought vpon the deceytes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.</note> and crueltie of his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, he ſayde: Fearefulneſſe, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling are come vpon me: and an horrible dread of death hath ouerwhelmed me. By the which he was made ſo timerous, and ſo fearefull, that he ſayde: O that I had winges like a Doue, for then would I flie away, and be at reſt. What was therfore done to ſo valiant a Worthie, that ſo chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhly he ſhould feare death? This feare of it ſelfe is not impietie, but it is partly a puniſhment of impietie. For if man had not ſinned, he had not béene ſubiect to the feare of death. This part therefore of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhement, is left euen in the moſt holye men: firſt, that they maye acknowledge their naturall impietie, by the which they haue deſerued euerlaſting puniſhment, if God for Chriſts ſake had not forgiuen the ſame. Furthermore, that they maye be ſtyrred to the more ardencie of prayer and faith. So <hi>IONAS</hi> alſo, although he were ſo excellent a Prophete, that by his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching he reſtored the decayed kingdome of <hi>Iſraell</hi> (as it is written in the xiiij. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8711:43"/> of the fourth booke of kings.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.</note>) Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, he is nowe compaſſed about with ſo great feare of death, that in dying, he is more cowardly and effeminate, than any common or raſcall Souldiour. But God would exerciſe him in this feare, that he might know his owne eſtate, and ſo be ſtirred the more earneſtly to pray.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, let vs not feare our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the perill of death, but rather let vs haue a ſure truſt, hauinge reſpect vnto Chriſt the ſonne of God, who hauing ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the feare of death, hath deliuered vs from the malediction of this feare, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we be wrapped and tangled in the ſame: yet notwithſtanding, we ſhall not periſhe, but be ſaued for Chriſtes ſake.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>IONAS</hi> is not onely vexed with grieuous feare of death, but alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payreth of hys corporall lyfe: I am caſt (ſayth he) out of thy ſight, that is, thou haſt no more reſpect vnto me, to preſerue me in this life: neyther ſhall I ſée any more thy holy temple, that is, I am conſtrained in this Whale to die, that I may go no more to the flocke of thy Church, in thy temple.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8711:44"/>
                  <p>What is the cauſe therefore, that the Prophete diſpayreth of his lyfe? where is his fayth? Coulde he beléeue that GOD would ſaue his ſoule, and not beléeue alſo, that he would preſerue and ſaue his body? Can not God rayſe vp men from death to lyfe? how could he not than preſerue thoſe in lyfe which are yet liuing? Did he not ſaue the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the redde ſea? howe than coulde hée not ſaue <hi>IONAS</hi> in the Whales belly? Theſe and ſuch like might be obiected to the prophet diſpayring of his corporal life in the Whales belly. But the prophet by this deſperation ſheweth foorth no part of wicked incredulitie, or diſtruſt, no more than <hi>Paule</hi> did, when he ſayde, we were grieued out of meaſure paſſing ſtrength,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> ſo greatly that we diſpaired euen of lyfe. Alſo we receyued an aunſwere of death in our ſelues. For there is two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of deliuerance or ſaluation from death. The one is corporall, the other is ſpiritual. And euerye one truely which beleueth in Chriſt, hath the certaine promiſe of the ſpirituall and heauenly ſaluation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce from death. For Chriſt hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8711:44"/> death, and ſayth: Euerye one which béeleueth in me,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6</note> ſhall not die for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Wherefore, we muſt in no wyſe doubt or diſpayre of this deliueraunce, and ſaluation. For whoſoeuer diſpayreth of the ſame, ſhall die for euer. The other is the corporall lyfe, the which although it hath béene promiſed, and is perfourmed by God towardes manye: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, wée haue not a generall promiſe at the handes of God, that euery one which beléeueth in Chriſt, ſhall alwayes corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally be deliuered from the perils of death. Wherfore, ſéeing this externe, and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deliueraunce hath not a certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, it can not certainly be looked for, but we muſt committe our will to the will of God. Wherevpon we may gather, that our Prophete <hi>IONAS</hi> diſpayred not of the true and eternall ſaluation, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, which hath a certaine promiſe in the ſéede of the woman, and in the ſéede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which is Chriſt. As touching the corporall ſaluation and deliueraunce, ſéeing it hath not a certaine, and expreſſe promiſe, it cannot conceyue a certayne,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:45"/> and vndoubted truſt, but it muſt call vpon God, and repoſe, and commit the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the deliueraunce to his will. For ſo Chriſt taught vs by his praier, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compaſſed about with externe and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall perils (from the which to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we haue no certaine promiſe) ſhoulde pray vnto God that he woulde vouchſafe corporally to defende and deliuer vs. Let this cup paſſe (ſayth our ſauiour Chriſt) from me:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note> yet not as I will, but as thou wilt. This if we doe with hart and minde, then ſhall wée oftentimes haue a deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce out of perill vnlooked for, when all hope is gone, euen as it happened to <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS,</hi> to the thrée yong men in the fierie Ouen in <hi>Babilon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Daniel.</hi> 3.</note> to <hi>Daniell, Dauid,</hi> and ſuch lyke. Yea, in all our trouble God will make a way in the midſt of the ſame, whereby we may eſcape: But if this deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce happen not vnto vs: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe our celeſtiall deliueraunce is moſt ſure and certaine, by the which, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beleueth in Chriſt, and calleth vpon the father in his name, ſhall neuer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8711:45"/>
                  <p>Now it foloweth in the other verſes, what the Prophete did in ſo great feare of death, and deſperation of life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶But thou, O Lorde my God,<note place="margin">The Text.</note> haſt brought vp my life againe out of corruption, when my ſoule fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within me, I thought vppon the Lorde: and my prayer came in vnto thee, euen into thy holye temple. They that hold of vaine vanities will forſake his mercye. But I will doe thee ſacrifice, with the voyce of thankesgiuing, and will paye that which I haue vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for why? ſaluation commeth of the Lord. And the Lord ſpake vnto the fiſhe, and it caſt out IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS againe vpon the drie lande.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THe Prophete hath rehearſed the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles &amp; afflictions, yea, the flames of hell fire with the which he was tormented in the Whales bellie. Nowe followeth the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the Canticle or Pſalme, in the which the Prophet ſheweth what he did to
<pb facs="tcp:8711:46"/> obteyne delyuerance from ſuch narrowe ſtrayts, and to ſlake the tormenting heate and rage of hell fire. Although (ſayth hée) I went downe to the bottome of the hilles, and was barred in with earth: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge, thou, O Lorde God haſt brought my lyfe againe out of corruption. But haſt thou deliuered mée, I doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or rather diſpairing? No truly: I was not ydle in the Whales bellye, but when my ſoule was troubled within me, I remembred thée, O Lord, that my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er might come to thy holy temple.</p>
                  <p>We ſée here, that the Prophet in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tréeme neceſſitie had no other reſpect and regarde than to the Lorde himſelfe, to whome he came by earneſt and faythfull inuocation and prayer. Whereas many of vs being ſet in affliction and trouble, make haſte to impacience, to curſſing, &amp; to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of god. But by this way we obtaine not deliuerance, but our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; miſerie is the more increaſed. For if we couet to be preſerued and deliuered in aduerſity and trouble we muſt make haſt to pray vnto the Lorde. For inuocation is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8711:46"/> the waye by the which we purchaſe vnto vs true deliuerance. Euery one, ſayth the Prophet <hi>Ioell,</hi> which inuocateth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioell.</hi> 2.</note> or calleth vpon the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaued. The which ſaying, being once vttered by the Prophet <hi>Ioell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Actes.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> is alſo repeated by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Paule:</hi> and therfore worthy to be noted. There is nothing that ſéemeth more eaſie than to call vppon the name of the Lord. For what worke can be more ſleight and eaſie than the tongue to ſpeake, and ſaye: Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c. Yea, the children and Infantes can vtter theſe wordes. But childiſhe inuocation is one, and true and earneſt inuocation is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. The one is moſt eaſie, the other is moſt harde. I remember a certaine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſayde: there is nothing more harde than to praye and inuocate the name of God. For it is an eaſie matter to recite the words of prayer. But to pray and call tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the name of God is a great worke and painefull labour. For no man can call truly vpon God, except he bée firſt of all in the fauour of God, and reconciled vnto him. For how ſhouldeſt thou call vppon or
<pb facs="tcp:8711:47"/> praye vnto him, whome thou hateſt and knoweſt to be thine enimie. For thou canſt not be in Gods fauour and reconciled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, vnleſſe thou repent thée trulye of thy ſinnes. And in repenting aright, we muſt firſt acknowledge our ſinnes and wickedneſſe, and auoyde them. Then we muſt beleue that our ſinnes are put away by Chriſt and forgiuen, by the which faith there followeth a true obedience towards God in euery calling. Here let vs conſider how harde a thing it is, to call vppon God aright in aduerſitie. For no man calleth truly vppon him, but he which repenteth him of his ſinnes, flieth the ſame, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth firmely that he hath frée remiſſion in Chriſt, and then giueth himſelfe wholy to the obedience of god. But what ſéemeth more difficult vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than to hate ſinne, to flie the ſame, and to follow the works of righteouſneſſe. Let no man therfore think that he is called to an eaſie or light worke, when hée is called to inuocation of God and prayer. Theſe things are ſet before vs not that we ſhoulde be terrified, or diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged from inuocation, but that we ſhould
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8711:47"/> be ſtirred to earneſt, true, and feruent prayer.</p>
                  <p>Our Prophet <hi>IONAS</hi> is ſet here for an enſample vnto vs. For he is caſt into the ſea for his ſinne, bicauſe he fled from the preſence of the Lorde, and obeyed not his calling. He ſawe therfore in the bellye of the Whale the wrath of God to follow his diſobedience. What doth he therefore? He beginneth to crie vnto the Lorde, and to call vpon God. But God is angrye. He is therefore conſtrayned firſt of all, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge hys ſinne, and to attribute vnto God the glorye of righteouſneſſe, namely, bicauſe God iuſtly puniſhed him with ſo great and daungerous perils: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had he done vniuſtly if he had ſuffered him to haue periſhed euerlaſtinglye. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing acknowledged his ſinne, he beléeued certainely that by the promiſed ſéede of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> (which was Ieſus Chriſt) hée ſhoulde haue frée remiſſion and pardon for the ſame. Then in hart he promiſed obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto God, that he would euer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſerue him, and neuer runne away again as he had done before. Theſe things
<pb facs="tcp:8711:48"/> being done, hée might boldlye come vnto God, call vpon his name, and looke for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance out of the bellie of the Whale.</p>
                  <p>But ſome man will ſaye, many call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon God, which notwithſtanding are not deliuered from their corporall trouble. Did not Chriſt himſelfe call vppon God the father that the cup of his paſſion might paſſe awaye from him:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note> and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Chriſt was not deliuered from the externall croſſe? Steuen called vpon Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Actes.</hi> 7.</note> and yet notwithſtanding he was ſtoned. We muſt ſo thinke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of inuocation, that although externall ſaluation happen not alwayes: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding eternall ſaluation ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes happen to the true caller vppon God. So Chriſt was not deliuered from the externall croſſe, but yet he was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from death it ſelfe, and obteyned a name aboue all names. So <hi>Steuen</hi> was not deliuered from the ſtoning, but neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he was deliuered from death and hell, and when he ſaw Ieſus Chriſt at the right hande of God, he was receyued of him into the fellowſhip of his kingdome.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:8711:48"/>
                  <p>But how did <hi>IONAS</hi> behaue himſelfe towardes God for the wonderfull benifite of his deliuerance? Surely he offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God the acceptable ſacrifice of thankes giuing, as appeareth by the texte: I will doe vnto thée, ſacrifice, with the voyce of thankeſgiuing. And before it is ſayde, they that holde of vaine vanities will forſake his mercie. By the which words the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete maketh a difference betwéene the thankfulneſſe of the godly, and the than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſgiuinge of the wicked. The wicked, when they receyue anye benifite at the handes of God, they referre it to their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles, and to their hypocriticall worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, and ſeruice. The Ethnicke or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then being deliuered from a Feuer, or any other diſeaſe, runneth ſtraight way to <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> and for his health offereth to him the offring and ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing. The hypocrite being deliuered from the paine of tooth ache, goeth to Saint <hi>Appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,</hi> to whome for the eaſe receyued, he offereth the ſacrifice of thankeſgiuinge. The Monke being deliuered from the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of waters, maketh haſte to S. <hi>Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8711:49"/> or to his Maſſe where he yéeldeth the ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing. But what ſaith the Prophete here of ſuch. They that holde of vaine things (ſayth he) will forſake the mercy of the Lorde. That is, they which followe vayne Idolles, and hypocriticall worſhippinges in offering thankes vnto God, theſe forſake the mercy of the Lorde, which he beſtowed vpon them, and make themſelues vnworthie of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>But I (ſayth the Prophete) will doe to thée ſacrifice, with the voyce of thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, and will perfourme that which I haue vowed, for why? ſaluation commeth of the Lorde. That is, I in offering the ſacrifice of prayſe and thankeſgiuing will not do as the wicked and hypocrytes doe, which worſhip God with abhominable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, with vaine worſhippings, and fained inuentions. But I will offer vnto thée my true God, and ſauiour, the voyce of praiſe: yea, I will prayſe thy name for euer, and will ſet foorth the glorie of the ſame vnto all men. I will preach and proclayme thy clemencie, and mercie, ſo long as I liue. And I will pay my vowes, that is, I will
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8711:49"/> doe thoſe thinges which I ought to doe. I will not deuiſe and inuent fayned ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as the hypocrites doe, but I will doe thoſe dueties which God requireth at my handes to be done. If it pleaſe God to ſend me againe vnto <hi>Niniue,</hi> I will not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, but with heart and minde, I wyll ſéeke the performance of his will. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample therefore of the Prophete <hi>IONAS</hi> is ſet foorth vnto vs, to the ende we might learne to offer the true ſacrifice of than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſgiuing vnto God, for thoſe benifites which we receyue at his handes, whether they pertayne to the bodie or to the minde, that we may continually abyde in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the Lorde.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The thirde Chapter.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen the worde of the Lorde came to IONAS againe, ſaying: vp,<note place="margin">The text.</note> and get thee to Niniue that great Citie, and preache vnto them the preaching
<pb facs="tcp:8711:50"/> that I bade thee. So IONAS aroſe, and went to Niniue, at the Lordes commaundement. Niniue was a great Citie vnto God, namely, of three daies iorney. And IONAS went to, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the Citie, euen a dayes iourney.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IONAS</hi> at the length eſcaped oute of the Whales belly, that is, from extréeme death and hell. For after that <hi>IONAS</hi> had repented, and called vpon the name of the Lorde by true fayth, the Whale was conſtrayned to caſt him out aliue, and to let him go frée. For God being reconciled vnto vs, all creatures are conſtrayned to miniſter vnto vs, and to ſerue our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and thoſe thinges alſo which before were hurtfull vnto vs, bring then muche profite and commoditie with them to oure great comfort and conſolation.</p>
                  <p>Therefore nowe conſequently the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie to the which <hi>IONAS</hi> after hys deliueraunce was called by the mouth of God, muſt be declared. For he is now ſent of God (as he was before) to <hi>Niniue,</hi> to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8711:50"/> ende he might preach there the deſtruction of the Citie. Vp (ſayth he) and get thée to <hi>Niniue</hi> that great Citie. As concerning the greatneſſe of the Citie of <hi>Niniue,</hi> it was before declared. And now the things which are to bée conſidered in this place, are theſe. Firſt, <hi>IONAS</hi> after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce is not placed of God in a ſoft Fetherbed, but he is ſent to preache the worde of God in <hi>Niniue,</hi> which was a worke not onely laborious, but alſo daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. Here therefore wée are taught whervnto we are called of God, and what we ought to doe, when we haue receyued any benifite at his hande.</p>
                  <p>For we truly are ſo corrupted by nature with ſinne, that after we haue receiued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifites, we are more peruerſe, and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto God, than we were before. And we ſée by experience, that they which haue come from extréeme beggery and penury, to great riches and poſſeſſions, and from the dunghill to Nobilitie, haue béene then more inſolent and vnthankefull then they were before. But the example of <hi>IONAS</hi> in this place, teacheth vs true obedience,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:51"/> and pietie. For after that we are deliuered out of great perils and daungers, we muſt not be ydle, neyther muſt we then begin to diſpiſe God, but rather it is our duties to obey God, and his calling, and to bée thankefull for thoſe benifits that wée haue receyued at his handes. In the fift Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth to the man that was reſtored to hys helth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> Behold, thou art now made whole, go, and ſinne no more, leaſt ſome worſe thing happen vnto thée. So <hi>IONAS</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſéemed to ſay within himſelfe: beholde, thou art now deliuered from the perill of death, and the goulfe of hell, ſée therefore, that thou be no more diſobedient, but obey the calling of God, leaſt a worſe thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto thée. Euen ſo it is our partes to thinke alſo, after that we are deliuered ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the perill of pouertie, from the perill of infirmitie, or from the perill of death. Beholde, thou haſt receyued an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent benefite at the handes of God, bée not therfore vnthankefull, but ſéeke by all meanes thou canſt to ſhewe a thankefull minde by dooing thy dutie. For God moſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8711:51"/> liberally beſtoweth his benifites, not that we ſhoulde be worſe, but to the ende wée ſhould be better. But and it we abuſe the benifites of God, as riches to luxvrie, and to fulfill our pleaſure: wyne, to drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and health, to diſhoneſtie and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked lyfe: then let vs looke for nothing elſe but to be depriued, not onely of theſe corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benifits, but alſo of heauenly treaſure and felicitie, and to periſh with euerlaſting paine and puniſhment. Wherefore, let vs conſider, that after the benifits receyued, we are called to thankfulneſſe, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the which, if we perfourme we ſhall prouoke the Lorde to beſtowe greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifites vpon vs. Furthermore, we muſt conſider in the example of <hi>IONAS,</hi> hys ſinguler obedience. For the Text ſayth, <hi>IONAS</hi> aroſe, and went to <hi>Niniue,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the worde of the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Before <hi>IONAS</hi> aroſe to flie from the preſence of God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 1</note> But nowe he ariſeth not to flie, but to obey the calling of the Lorde. What was the cauſe that <hi>IONAS</hi> is thus altered and chaunged, and that he is ſo prompt and readie to perfourme the wil
<pb facs="tcp:8711:52"/> and commaundement of God? Surelye, the affliction, perill, and trouble, was the cauſe, as hath béene alreadie at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. We ſée therefore what is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall reaſon, why God doth oftentymes lay croſſes, and ſundry afflictions vpon vs. <hi>IONAS</hi> would not ſimplye at the firſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the worde of the Lorde, he is caſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into the ſea, that ſéeing he would not by the worde, and in proſperitie, learne to obey, he might learne the ſame by croſſe in aduerſitie.</p>
                  <p>The lyke oftentimes happeneth vnto vs. For God firſt of all calleth vs being ſinners, and diſobedient, to righteouſneſſe and obedience by the preachinge of his worde when we are in proſperitie. But when we flie obedience, then he caſteth vs into the ſea of diuers afflictions, to the ende we might learne that, in aduerſitie and trouble, which we refuſed in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and eaſe. So the Lorde God of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſent to the Citizens of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> that they ſhould forſake their idolatrie, but when they woulde not obey his worde in libertie, they were conſtreyned to learne
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8711:52"/> obedience in captiuitie. Wherefore, when we flouriſhing in proſperitie are called to repentance, let vs not deſpiſe the voyce of the Lord, but let vs obey him in time, leaſt with the wicked wée be afflicted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ And he cried, ſaying:<note place="margin">The Text.</note> there are yet fortie dayes, and then ſhall Niniue be ouerthrowne.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>This is the ſermon which <hi>IONAS</hi> made in <hi>Niniue,</hi> being very briefe, and ſhort, if we haue reſpect to the number of the words, but if we conſider the ſentence, it is very long, and containeth much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Firſt of all let vs weye and conſider the place of the Citie, in the which <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> began to preache. When he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred (ſayth the text) into the citie euen a dayes iourney, and ſo forth. Therefore <hi>IONAS</hi> preached euen in the middeſt of the citie almoſt, not in the comming in, nor in the going forth, to the ende the fame of his ſermonde, or preachinge, might the more eaſily be ſpred among al the citizens
<pb facs="tcp:8711:53"/> and inhabitants thereabout. For the word of the Lorde muſt be preached, not to a fewe men onely, neyther in an obſcure place, but to all men openlye, to the ende no man might haue excuſe. Herevppon it came to paſſe, and was accuſtomed, that alwayes from the beginning of the world the word of God was preached in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe Monarchies &amp; Cities of the earth. For as <hi>IONAS</hi> could not go from houſe to houſe generally throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie of <hi>Niniue,</hi> but ſtoode in a conuenient place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> City, that the fame of his preaching might come to all men, euen ſo the word of the Lord is not wont to be caried to euery corner of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery region, but it is reuealed &amp; publiſhed in the ſpeciall and principall kingdomes, that by them the fame thereof might be ſpred abrode throughout the whole world, that no man might haue excuſe. So the worde of the Lorde was preached in the time of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which were in thoſe places and tymes the ſpeciall kingdomes. So likewyſe in the Monarchie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> by <hi>Daniell.</hi> And ſo the worde of God was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8711:53"/> preached in <hi>Rome</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they which lurke in woods and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes haue no excuſe, that the worde of God is not brought peculiarlye vnto them by the Prophetes, and Apoſtles: but it is ſufficient that the word of God is preached openly and fréely in publike places, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the fame maye be ſpred into all places. But this is not ſpoken to the ende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes in little townes &amp; vilages ſhoulde be neglected &amp; abrogated. For our aunceſtors appointed &amp; ordeined Pariſhes with their great coſt, and the inhabitants of villages to pay their tenthes, that they might haue Paſtors appointed vnto them.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore, they which care not to haue Paſtors, or Preachers, which might ſhew the worde of the Lorde vnto them, but kéepe the tenth and tribute, to themſelues. Theſe I ſay are open théeues and ſpoilers of the Church of God. But they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed and ſpoken, to the ende we maye knowe that no man in the whole earth, whereſoeuer hée dwelleth, might haue any excuſe of his impietie, wickedneſſe, or ignoraunce, bicauſe that, although the
<pb facs="tcp:8711:54"/> worde of God bée not preached in euerye mountaine and woode: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is preached in the ſpeciall places of the earth. It grieueth not the Merchaunt man to make a long and daungerous voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age from <hi>Englande</hi> to <hi>Spaine,</hi> to <hi>Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> to <hi>India,</hi> to fetche his merchaundiſe thence for aduantage and gaine, and ſhall it grieue vs to ſéeke for the hearing of the word of God,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 13.</note> that precious pearle &amp; iewel, bicauſe the place where it is preached, is farre diſtant from vs? God forbid. For if that we be ſo ſlowe in ſeking for that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſure, the muck and droſſe of this world which is ſo dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſought for, ſhal condemne vs in the day of iudgement.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, wée muſt alſo wey and note the maner of <hi>IONAS</hi> preachinge, for the text ſayth: he cried. We muſt not thinke here, that he cried out, or raged with exclamation as mad men doe, or ſuch as be drunke, but rather that he ſpake plainely placing his wordes without ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie. Wherefore, it is the dutie of all Paſtors and Preachers, after the example of <hi>IONAS,</hi> to auoyde and eſchewe all
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8711:54"/> obſcuritie in their doctrine, which teacheth not euidently &amp; plainly, the way of truth. Such were the Sophiſters, and others, in old time, which indeuoured themſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſpeake obſcurely, miſtically, and darkely of religion. Such alſo are the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, and enimies of Gods truth, which publiſh and ſet forth all their ceremonies and ſeruice in an vnknowne tongue. Wherfore, although they howle, chaunt, pipe, and bable much in the Latine tongue before the common people in their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: yet notwithſtanding they doe but whiſper, and talke to them that haue no eares. They doe but ſpeake in the ayre,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> as witneſſeth Saint Paule. For if the trump giue an vncertaine ſounde, who ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe to the battayle? Euen ſo ye (ſayth the Apoſtle) ſpeaking with tongues, except ye ſpeake wordes that haue ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, howe ſhall it be vnderſtoode what is ſpoken. For ſo the ſimple and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, maye ſaye, <hi>Amen,</hi> to him that curſeth, when he ſhoulde bleſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let euerye man deſire with Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> rather to ſpeake fiue wordes in the
<pb facs="tcp:8711:55"/> congregation to the information of other, than ten thouſand words with the tongue.</p>
                  <p>Nowe let vs heare what the Prophete preached. There are yet fortie days (ſayth he) and then ſhal <hi>Niniue</hi> be ouerthrowne. A ſhort ſermon trulye to be made in ſo great a citie: yet notwithſtanding ſo great in effect, that <hi>IONAS</hi> thereby ſtoode not only in perill of his lyfe, but alſo in hazard of his good name and fame. For the king of the <hi>Niniuets,</hi> and his Citizens, might haue ſurmiſed by this ſermon, that <hi>IONAS</hi> with forreine enimies had priuilye conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the deſtruction of the Citie, eyther by fire in the night, or elſe by tumult, and ſo might haue accuſed him of ſedition, and deſtroyed him. Further, if they had belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that it was the worde of God which he preached (as they did in déede) and the ſame had not bene fulfilled, then myght they haue accuſed <hi>IONAS</hi> to be a vayne and a lying Prophet. Neuertheleſſe, the Prophet is not diſcouraged by theſe perils of his life and fame, but procéedeth in his calling with obedience, ſhewing that, to the <hi>Niniuets</hi> which he was commaunded
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8711:55"/> of God to declare. By the which example we are admoniſhed, that in following our vocation and calling, we ſhoulde rather haue a conſideration of the wrath of God towardes diſobedience, than of perill and daunger which happen vnto vs by diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. For if God be angry with vs for diſobedience, then wée maye aſſure our ſelues to ſuffer perill, in the which vnleſſe we repent, we maye looke for nothing but euerlaſting diſtruction. But if we obey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> calling of god, although moſt daungerous perils &amp; horrible deſtruction lye before our eies ready to deuour vs: yet neuertheleſſe, they ſhall eyther not happen vnto vs, or if they doe happen vnto vs, God ſhall my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly, ſaue, defende, and deliuer vs. Examples of this, we haue <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the deſert, <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> in the Lions denne, <hi>Iob</hi> on the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, the thrée children in the fierie Ouen, and many other. But what ſhall we ſay to the ſermon of <hi>IONAS,</hi> which ſayde, that <hi>Niniue</hi> ſhould be deſtroyed within fortie dayes, and yet was not deſtroyed. Is the Prophet therfore a lyar? Truly this was
<pb facs="tcp:8711:56"/> the ſpeciall cauſe why the Prophet fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the preſence of the lord, &amp; would not preache deſtruction to the <hi>Niniuets,</hi> For he conſidered that if they ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, the Citie ſhould continue in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate, and he counted a vayne and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prophete. And yet notwithſtanding, being exerciſed with croſſe and trouble, he obeyeth the calling of God, and publikely preacheth, that the Citie ſhall be deſtroyed within fortie dayes. How then is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie to be vnderſtoode and cléered of a lye? Some diſſolue it after this ſort, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that there are two maner of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies,<note place="margin">Two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies.</note> namely the prophecie of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the prophecie of commination or threatning. The prophecie of predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is that, which by no meanes maye be retracted: ſuch was the prophecy of the <hi>Meſsias</hi> to come, and of the publiſhing of the Goſpell throughout the whole worlde. This is the prophecie of predeſtination, that is, without any certayne condition, which coulde not eyther by anye mans power, wiſedome, or wickedneſſe, be ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or fruſtrate. The prophecie of commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8711:56"/> is, which threatneth only the euill of puniſhments to come, the which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding may be ſtayed and preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the repentance of the hearers: and ſuch is this Prophecie of the deſtruction of the <hi>Niniuets.</hi> And theſe things truly are rightly ſpoken of the prophecie of commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, if ſo be that they be rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode. The which, that we may in déede, let vs vnderſtande the difference betwene the lawe and the Prophetes, that we may knowe which is the true ſenſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, and threatnings, which pertayne to the lawe. For the lawe of God, doth manifeſtly require the perfite fulfilling of the commaundements of God, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute righteouſneſſe alſo. And if any man doe not fulfill the commaundementes of God perfitely, neyther doth performe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute righteouſneſſe, then doth the lawe curſe him, and pronounce him to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as well of corporall as of eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. After the ſame maner alſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of the law require righteouſneſſe, the which except a man obſerue, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, both corporall and ſpirituall afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:8711:57"/> are threatned vnto him. But the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell interpreteth theſe Prophecies, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and maledictions of Chriſt, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the prophecies, and threatnings of the lawe ſhall procéede and fall vppon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent perſons, but bicauſe Chriſt hath ſatiſfied for ſinne, and hath reconciled vs vnto God the father, therefore he which repenteth, and turneth by fayth vnto Chriſt, is no more ſubiect to the threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and curſes of the lawe.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore this Prophecie of <hi>IONAS</hi> alſo ſaying: There are yet fortie dayes, and then <hi>Niniue</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, is to be vnderſtoode with this condicion: if ye doe not conuert, repent, and amende.</p>
                  <p>For, that ſuch prophecies and threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are ſo to be vnderſtoode, many other places of Scripture doe teſtifie. As thys: But if that people doe repent them of their euill,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiere.</hi> 48.</note> I alſo will repent me of the plague that I haue deuiſed agaynſt them. Here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Hiere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> teacheth that the prophecy of deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or plague, is vnderſtoode with this condition: if the Iewes doe not repent.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8711:57"/> For if they had repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted at the preachings of the Prophetes, then <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> had not bene deſtroyed. The Lorde alſo by the Prophete <hi>Ezechiell</hi> ſayth, I liue,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>EZechiel.</hi> 18.</note> and will not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he turne from his wickedneſſe, and liue. Here agayne, the Lorde plainlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, how he woulde haue his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to bée vnderſtoode, by the which, hée threatneth death, or deſtruction vnto ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. For he ſayth often times, to a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to a Citie, or to a priuate man: thou haſt grieuouſlye ſinned agaynſt mée, by committing this or that ſinne. Wherefore, thou muſt of neceſſitie die, not only corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, but alſo eternally. This is a moſte true and certaine prophecie: but yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, we muſt vnderſtande it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. Howe? God himſelfe in this place of <hi>Ezechiell</hi> ſweareth by himſelfe, by his lyfe, that he woulde not ſimplye haue the ſinner to bée damned, but rather that he repent him of his ſinne, and liue. And moſt ſure &amp; certayne it is, that the ſinner ſhould dye eternally if he did not repent, but if he doe repent, then is the plague before
<pb facs="tcp:8711:58"/> threatned, retracted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth. If we denie him, he remayneth faythfull, he can not deny him ſelfe. And agayne he ſayth: The giftes and calling of God are ſuch,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.</note> that it cannot repent him of them, that is, god repenteth him not of his promiſes. All theſe thinges teach, that the promiſes of the Goſpell as concerning the redemption from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting death, are moſt ſure, and irreuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But the promiſes and threatnings of the lawe maye be retracted, not from the impenitent, vppon whome they remayne moſt firme and immutable, but from the godlye and penitent, which turne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto Chriſt by fayth, which cannot deny himſelfe to thoſe that beléeue in him. Wherefore, when our ſinnes doe pricke our conſciences, and accuſe vs before God, and doe condemne vs to euerlaſting death, let vs turne to the goſpel, to Chriſt, who being made accurſed for vs, hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed euerlaſting benediction to vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">The text.</note>¶ And the people of Niniue belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God, and proclaymed faſting,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8711:58"/> and arayed themſelues in ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, as well the great as the ſmall of them.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>This place of the repentance of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuets,</hi> is worthie the remembrance, and diligently to be noted: and it is not onely knowne to the godly teachers, but alſo to the hypocrytes, ſacrificing Prieſtes, and Monkes. For theſe men alwayes in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of repentaunce, are woont to bring foorth ſtreight way the example of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuets,</hi> and to exhort their Church to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent by theyr example. But they chooſe out in this place, onely thoſe things which make more to the ſtabliſhing of hipocriſie, than to the ſetting foorth of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. For that which the text ſayth (they beléeued in the Lorde) they couertly omit, and take onely for their purpoſe, faſting, and ſackcloth, and perſwade themſelues that they preach true repentaunce, when they vrge the church to faſt certain dayes, and to go woolwarde without linnen. For they thinke that by eating of bread onely, and by drinking water, &amp; by going wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb facs="tcp:8711:59"/> their ſinnes are done away before God, and that theſe are merits, for the which God doth omitte the fault and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſinne. And in the meane time they make no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the true acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of their ſinnes, of the true fayth in Chriſt (for the which fayth alone, God is mercifull vnto vs) and of the true fruites of fayth, and repentaunce. But this place conteyneth a manifeſt and plaine doctrine of true repentaunce. Wherfore, let vs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the dreames of Monkes, and learne out of this place true repentaunce, which God regardeth, and which ſaueth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth vs in extréeme perils.</p>
                  <p>And firſt of all, before we come to the explication of repentance, we muſt know that the repentaunce is not in vaine in the Church, but of great force before God, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning for vs the true and euerlaſting ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Nouation heretikes.</note>There were ſometymes certaine here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes called <hi>Nouations,</hi> which left to the ſinner after he was baptiſed, and had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued once remiſſion of his ſinnes, no place of repentance. But the error of theſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8711:59"/> men is manifeſtly refuted, by many eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent teſtimonies of Scripture.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiere.</hi> 3.</note> As in the thirde of <hi>Hieremie,</hi> where the Lord ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the people thus: Commonly when a man putteth away his wyfe, and ſhe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from him, and maryeth with another, then the queſtion is: ſhould he reſort vnto hir any more after that? Is not his fielde then defiled, and vncleane? But as for thée, thou haſt played the harlot with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny louers:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiere.</hi> 18.</note> yet turne againe to me ſayth the Lorde. And againe he ſayth: If that nation repent, I will alſo repent. The Parables alſo in the .xv.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 15.</note> of <hi>Luke</hi> teach the ſame thing, by the loſt ſhéepe, by the loſt grote, by the prodigall ſonne. Wherefore let vs vnderſtand, that true repentaunce is moſt acceptable vnto God, and auayle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſaluation, ſometimes corporally, as appeareth here by the example of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuets,</hi> but alwayes eternally.</p>
                  <p>Let vs now therfore ſée what we muſt doe, when we haue ſinned, and for ſinne deſerued, moſt grieuous puniſhment, both corporall, and eternall, as the <hi>Niniuetes</hi> deſerued. Firſt, let vs truely repent, and
<pb facs="tcp:8711:60"/> wée ſhall obtaine not onely remiſſion of ſinne, but alſo releaſe of puniſhment. It is not neceſſary that we ſhould be curious or muche inquiſitiue, when as this preſent place brieflye (yet notwithſtanding, both godly and truely) teacheth vs the true and perfite way to repent. For the Scripture ſayth: the people of <hi>Niniue</hi> beleued in the Lorde. This is the true and certaine way of repentaunce to beléeue in the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>The which thing being vttered and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Epicures, and contemners of true godlyneſſe, can ſcarce refraine laughter, eſtéeming that there is nothing more eaſie to be done, than to beleue in the Lord. But I would not that we ſhould erre. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth in the Lorde, is required of vs, let vs knowe and vnderſtande that a worke, no leſſe hard, heauenly, and diuine, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of vs, than was the creation of heauen and earth. If a man ſhould ſay vnto thée, make heauen and earth, thou wouldeſt thinke that a worke impoſſible, and aboue thy ſtrength were required of thée. But when it is ſayde: beléeue in the Lorde, a thing no leſſe impoſſible is required of thée
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8711:60"/> then the creation of heauen and earth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 19.</note> Impoſſible I meane it is to fleſhe &amp; bloud, but not impoſſible to the ſpirite, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall force. The which thing to explicate, let vs take the example of the <hi>Niniuetes.</hi> For where as it is ſayde, that they belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lorde, it is ment that they belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſermon which <hi>IONAS</hi> made at the commaundement of the Lorde, that it was the true, diuine, and heauenly voyce of God. But how hard a thing it was to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue this, many thinges doe declare.<note place="margin">4. <hi>King.</hi> 14.</note> For firſt of all, if we haue reſpect to the perſon of <hi>IONAS,</hi> although he were counted a great Prophete among the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> yet notwithſtanding, he was not of ſo great authoritie among the <hi>Niniuetes,</hi> whiche were vncircumciſed Gentiles. It is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell therefore that they ſayde not, what haue we to do with that Iew, that ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? what meaneth that fugitiue, and runnagate fellow? hath God talked more with him than with our Biſhops and high Prieſtes? If it had béene the purpoſe of God to ouerthrowe our Citie, woulde hée not ſooner haue reuealed it to our King, or
<pb facs="tcp:8711:61"/> to ſome of our chiefe rulers in the Citie, than to this runneawaye Iewe. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Citizens, nor the Magiſtrates, nor the King himſelfe, obiected any ſuche thing to <hi>IONAS,</hi> but ſimply beléeued his worde, as the worde of God. Wherefore, it is manifeſt that they were ſtirred vp to beléeue, not by humane power, but by heauenly force, euen by the ſpirit of God. Furthermore, if we marke the text well, when it ſayth: They beléeued in the Lord, it ſhall eaſily appeare that fayth is not a humane worke, but a diuine worke. For to beléeue in the Lorde comprehendeth thrée things. 1 The firſt is, to beléeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lawe of God is true, when it reproueth vs of ſinne, and condemneth vs for ſinne, and pronounceth vs to be guiltie of all, as well corporall as eternall puniſhmentes. But to beléeue this, is not a worke of the fleſhe, but a worke of the ſpirite. Let vs beholde therefore the ſermon of <hi>IONAS.</hi> There are yet (ſayth hée) fortie dayes, and then ſhall <hi>Niniue</hi> be ouerthrowne. This is a ſermon of the lawe, which is in effect, as if he had ſayde: You <hi>Niniuets,</hi> ye are
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8711:61"/> vngodly men, and the moſte wicked ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the whole world. Wherfore, God within fortie dayes will ſo ouerthrowe, and deſtroye your Citie, that ye ſhall be caſt both body and ſoule into hell. To take ſuch a ſermon in good part, and to beléeue the ſame to be true, is not of the fleſh and bloude, but a worke of the holy ghoſt. For men being left and giuen ouer vnto their ſtrength cannot abyde to be reprehended, much leſſe to be tolde, that they ſhall bée damned. Wherefore, if they pacientlye beare reprehenſion, and acknowledge their ſinne and damnation, it is manifeſt that they are indewed with the power of the holy ghoſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, to beléeue in the Lorde, is to beléeue the promiſe made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as concerning Chriſt, that is, to beléeue that the remiſſion of our ſinnes, our lyfe, and ſaluation is eternall, true, and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But to beléeue this, cannot be brought to paſſe in man, but only by the holy ghoſt. For it is not a worke of the fleſh, or of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſedome, but only of the ſpirite of God. Let vs therefore once agayne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb facs="tcp:8711:62"/> of the ſermon of <hi>IONAS,</hi> There are yet (ſaith he) fortie daies, and then ſhal <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue</hi> be deſtroyed. Although this ſermon ſéemeth only to be a ſermon of the law: yet notwithſtanding, he which vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the lawe of God aryghte, he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth alſo that in this ſermon is contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſermon of the Goſpell of Chriſt. For <hi>Paule</hi> (as concerning the law) ſayth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Galath.</hi> 3.</note> The law is a ſchoolemaiſter vnto Chriſt. Whereſoeuer therfore the lawe doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, there doth it referre vs vnto Chriſt, that wée might be deliuered from damnation. Moreouer, S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth, The ſcripture (that is the law of the Lord) hath concluded al things vnder ſinne, that the promiſe of the faith of Chriſt Ieſus might be giuen to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleue: That is to ſay. The law bringeth vs to the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne, not that we ſhoulde periſh in ſinne, but that we ſhoulde be referred to Chriſt by fayth, and by him obtayne ſaluation. Alſo the Lorde by the mouth of <hi>Ezechiell</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.</note> I will not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he turne from his wickedneſſe and lyue. But the law threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8711:62"/> death to the ſinner, yet, not that hée ſhoulde periſhe by death, but to the ende he might be ſtirred vp to come vnto Chriſt by fayth, and ſo obtaine lyfe. So this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of <hi>IONAS</hi> includeth in it ſelfe the Goſpell of the ſéede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt. For he woulde not that the <hi>Niniuets</hi> ſhould periſhe, but that they ſhoulde be conuerted to the ſéede of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (which is Chriſt) by faith, and might haue in him remiſſion of ſinnes, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe. To beléeue this, is not a worke of the fleſh, but of the ſpirite.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, to beléeue in the Lorde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth alſo in it ſelfe, to beléeue the commaundementes of the Lorde to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, and that it is neceſſarie to exhibite vnto them obedience by faith, and to bring forth the true fruites of repentaunce, namely, the acknowledge of our ſinne and fayth in Chriſt. To doe this alſo, we are vnable without the ayde of Gods ſpirite. For we cannot truly obey the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, vnleſſe the Lorde encline our hartes therevnto by his holye ſpirite. Wherefore, when it is ſayd in the texte,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:63"/> that the <hi>Niniuets</hi> beléeued the Lorde, it meaneth not that they only had a light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and imagination of God, but it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that they ſhewed foorth theſe thrée things, namely, that they beléeued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ſinners, and that they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not only deſtruction, but alſo eternall damnation. Secondly, that they beléeued to receiue pardon and forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes for the ſeede of <hi>Abraham</hi> onelye (which was Chriſt) whoſe Prophete <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> was. Thirdly, it ſignifieth that they determined with themſelues euer after to auoyde ſinne, and to obey the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God. This is that true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which God regardeth, and which obteyneth remiſſion of ſinnes and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>What meaneth it then, that the <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets</hi> proclaime a faſt, and put on ſacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth? Theſe are not the true workes of repentaunce, but they are the externall ſignes of repentaunce. For faſting is not auayleable to put away ſinne,<note place="margin">The ende of faſting.</note> but ſerueth only to chaſtiſe the fleſhe, and to make it apt and obedient to heare the worde of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8711:63"/> God. Therefore when the <hi>Niniuets</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a faſting, they did it to the ende the Citizens might come ſober to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and euery man to doe his dutie. But whereas they did put on ſackecloth, (that is, baſe apparell) it is a ſigne and token of publike ſorrowe and griefe for ſinne, and an admonition to true repentance, which is the chiefeſt thing to be looked for, as ſhal appeare by the proclamation of the king.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ And tydinges came vnto the king of Niniue,<note place="margin">The Text.</note> which aroſe out of his ſeate, and did his apparell off, and put on ſackcloth, and ſate him downe in aſhes. And it was cryed and commaunded in Niniue by the authority of the king, and his Lordes, ſaying: See that neither man, nor beaſt, Oxe, or ſheepe taſte ought at all, and that they neyther feede nor drinke water: but put on ſackcloth both man and beaſt: and crie mightily vnto God. Yea, ſee that euerye man turne from his euill waye, and
<pb facs="tcp:8711:64"/> from the wickedneſſe that he hath in hande. Who can tell? God maye turne and repent, and ceaſe from his fierce wrath, that wee pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh not.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>The text here maketh no mention of the Kings name. But by what name ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he were called, he deſerued great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. For he was not adorned and bewtified onely with kingly vertues, but alſo with heauenly graces.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt of al, when tydings was brought vnto the King of the ſermon which <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> made, and of the ſtudie, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of the Citizens, he maketh not excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Prophete, he accuſeth him not of ſedition, and tumult, but beléeueth alſo himſelfe the worde of <hi>IONAS.</hi> The Prophete <hi>Hieremie</hi> reproueth the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> for their wickedneſſe and impietie,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiere.</hi> 26.</note> and ſayth, that vnleſſe they repent, it will come to paſſe that the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lorde ſhall be deſtroyed as <hi>Siloh</hi> was, and ſo forth. The hie Prieſtes then and the common people tooke him, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8711:64"/> woulde haue put him to death as a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, and ſedicious perſon. So ſome wicked tyrant would not haue wincked at the preaching of <hi>IONAS,</hi> when he ſayde the Citie ſhoulde bée ouerthrowne: but woulde haue apprehended him, and put him to death, as if he had bene of ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret conſpiracie to deſtroye the ſame at a ſodeine, by fire, or elſe to bring in the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie by night.</p>
                  <p>But the godly king of the <hi>Niniuetes,</hi> ſuſpected no ſuch thing in <hi>IONAS,</hi> but receyueth him as a true Prophete of the Lorde, and acknowledgeth his ſermon for the worde of God. For we may not thinke that this king was ſo ſimple, ſo raſhe, or ſo madde, that he would vnaduiſedly beléeue the wordes of this Prophet. And although in hearing Sermons, we muſt ſpecially note, not who ſpeaketh, but what is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: yet notwithſtanding, in great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and thinges pertayning to ſaluation, we muſt not raſhely credit euery ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which preacheth newe thinges with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out certaine and manifeſt teſtimonies. Proue (ſayth ſaint Paule) all things,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 5.</note> and
<pb facs="tcp:8711:65"/> kéepe that which is good. And ſaint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> Beléeue not euery ſpirite, but proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirits whether they be of God or no. So we muſt thinke of this godly king of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue,</hi> that he beléeued not raſhely the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>IONAS,</hi> but that he firſt proued who it was that preached theſe thinges, and what teſtimonies he had of his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For <hi>IONAS</hi> was neyther vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the king, nor to the Citizens of <hi>Niniue,</hi> but they knew him to be the true prophete of the Lord, bicauſe his fame was ſpred euen to <hi>Niniue,</hi> when as by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie the Kingdome of <hi>Iſraell</hi> was reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Ieroboam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4 <hi>Kin.</hi> 14.</note> as it is written in the booke of Kinges. Furthermore, the godly king knewe, that God woulde not ſuffer ſinne and wickedneſſe, to ſcape vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and that he was ſeuere in looking for repentaunce. Séeing therefore <hi>IONAS</hi> to haue certaine teſtimonies, that he was the prophete of the Lorde, and perceyuing how all thinges were corrupt in the Citie with wicked maners, he worthily recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Sermon of <hi>IONAS,</hi> as a diuine Oracle.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:8711:65"/>
                  <p>By the which example we are taught not to receyue the doctrine of euery one by and by (which boſteth himſelfe to be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete) as the worde of God, and not to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe by and by the prophecie of euery one, which ſayth, that he hath the ſpirit of God. For this were a great token of lightneſſe, to beléeue euery buſie bodie. But after that we knowe, that the worde ſet foorth, and expounded vnto vs, is the worde of God in déede, then we muſt beléeue the ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out al doubt or delay, that we may obtaine and enioy the ende of fayth, which is (as ſayth ſaint <hi>Peter</hi>) the ſaluation of oure ſoules.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, this king, when he hearde that <hi>Niniue,</hi> for ſinne ſhoulde bée ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, he preferreth not himſelfe before his Citizens, he iudgeth not himſelfe to be more iuſt than other men, but in repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, he putteth of his kingly robes, and Maieſtie, and putteth on the apparell of a mourner, repenting, and acknowledging his ſinne. For he put off his kinglike ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and clothed himſelfe with ſackcloth, which is a garment betokening repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce.
<pb facs="tcp:8711:66"/> Neyther doth he ſit in his throne, or chayre of eſtate, wrought with ſilke, with néedle worke, and with golde, but he ſitteth with the reſt of his ſubiectes in the duſt, that is, in filthie places, and vndec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, to teſtifie and declare, that he alſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and bewayled the common ſtate of the Citie. By the which example we are not taught, that kinges and princes, when they repent, ſhould forſake the office and rule of their kingdome,<note place="margin">The yoke of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerye.</note> &amp; go into a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and there put on a Coole. For hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or to this paſſe, Monkes brought Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces when they went about to repent, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them to forſake their kingly and princely calling, and to putte the yoke of Monkery vpon their neckes, to ſatiſfie for ſinne. This was great impietie and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable. But kinges and princes are here taught, when GOD reuealeth his wrath againſt ſinne, not to think that they by the priuiledge of their maieſtie, are iuſt before God, and that the rude and raſcall ſort, are onely wicked and vniuſt before him: no, rather, they are taught to thinke themſelues to be comprehended among the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8711:66"/> common ſort of men, of whom it is ſayde, Euery man is a lyar. Alſo:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.</note> All haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and gone out of the way, there is not one that doth good, no not one. And again, No man liuing ſhall bée iuſtified in thy ſight. Wherefore, from the king that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on his throne, to the begger that lyeth in the ſtreate, there is not one, but he hath ſinned and hath néede of the glory of God. We haue all néede of one Ieſus Chriſt, of whom euery one is partaker, according to the meaſure of his fayth, whether hée bée king, or ſubiect, maiſter, or ſeruaunt, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or ſonne, according to the ſaying of ſaint <hi>Paule:</hi> There is neyther Iewe nor Gentile, neyther Barbarous nor Sythia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 3.</note> neyther bonde nor frée, neyther man nor woman, but all are one in Chriſt Ieſu.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, the king is not content to doe penaunce himſelfe alone, and to begin to leade a new and godly life, but alſo he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituteth a puplike and generall ordinance in the Church, that other men likewiſe might imbrace godlineſſe. For firſt of all, he proclaymeth a generall faſt, not onely of men, but alſo of beaſtes: Sée (ſayth he)
<pb facs="tcp:8711:67"/> that neyther man, nor beaſt, oxe, or ſhéepe, taſte ought at all: and that they neyther féede, nor drinke water. Then hée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth them to put off their coſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and mourning wyſe to array them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſacke. Furthermore, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth them to praye generallye, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and crie mightily vnto the Lord. Laſt of all, he appoynteth a ſermon, or procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to be made of repentance, ſaying: Sée that euery man turne from his euill way, and from the wickedneſſe he hath in hande. Here we haue an excellent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this godly king, from whom al other kinges and princes, may take examples of their calling. There are manye which thinke that mundane or ſeculer princes (as they terme them) ought not to deale in matters Eccleſiaſticall, but onely in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters pollitique. But this example, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other examples of <hi>Dauid, Salomon,</hi> of <hi>Ioſophat,</hi> of <hi>Ioſias,</hi> and likewiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſayinges of holy ſcripture doe teſtifie, that princes ought ſpecially to haue a care of matters Eccleſiaſticall. It is not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at their handes to preache, but it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8711:67"/> at their handes to appoynt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and to ſée that the woorde of God be preached ſincerely. For it is not ynough for Princes, that they themſelues are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, godly, and vertuous, but they ought to labour, and to ſéeke by all meanes, that their ſubiectes may alſo be honeſt, godly, and vertuous. For as the good man of the houſe, hath not done his duetie, if he onely here ſermons, and leade a godly lyfe, but muſt alſo ſéeke to traine vp his familye in true godlineſſe and vertue: euen ſo kings and princes, haue not ſufficiently diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their duetie, in directing their owne footeſteps aright, vnleſſe they haue a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regard to the pathes of their ſubiects. But nowe let vs ſée by the Text, what things are here to be noted.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, the king with his Citizens are clothed in ſackcloth, &amp; ſit in the duſt while they go about to repent them of their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But what: are thoſe workes a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for ſinne? are ſackcloth and aſhes of ſuch force before God, that he reſpecteth them, and for them turneth from hys wrath and puniſhment? Nothing leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:8711:68"/> truely. For otherwiſe, it were but vaine that God had promiſed his ſonne from the beginning of the worlde, to be the ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſinne, and at the fulneſſe of tyme to haue ſent him to ſuffer death for ſinne. For he might then haue ſhewed vs ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and aſhes, by the which, our ſinnes might haue béene done awaye. But the matter is farre otherwiſe. For the ſinnes of the <hi>Niniuetes,</hi> and our ſinnes are farre greater than that, they ſhould be forgiuen of God by putting on of ſackcloth, or by ſitting in the duſt. It was neceſſarie to the ſatiſfying for ſinne, that the ſonne of God ſhould not put on ſackcloth, but that hée ſhould ſuffer death: that he ſhould not ſit in the duſt, but that he ſhould hange on the Croſſe. What is ment then by the ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and duſt, which the <hi>Niniuetes</hi> vſed? They are not thinges able to pacifie the wrath of God, but they are true ſignes of confeſſion of ſinnes, and argumentes of contricion, which is had for ſinne. In the King, the throne was a ſigne of maieſtie. In the Citizens, the hie and precious ſeats in the temple, were ſignes of dignitie. But
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8711:68"/> nowe the king placeth not himſelfe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely, in his kingly throne, but ſitteth with his Citizens in the duſt of the earth, or in baſe and vncomely ſeates, to the ende they might openly declare themſelues, for their ſinnes to be vnworthy before God of their maieſtie and dignitie, and to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued death and deſtruction. The King and his Citizens had their ſumptuous, and precious apparell on feſtiuall dayes, at ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and at other ſolemne méetinges, with the which, they did bewtifie themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and excell other men. But nowe they put on vile and baſe apparell, to the ende there might ſéeme to be no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the king, and his magiſtrates, and other common people: and alſo to declare that they thought themſelues vnworthie of their bodily apparell, by reaſon of their ſinnne.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſackcloth and aſhes, are not ſatiſfactions for ſinne, but they are onely argumentes of the acknowledging and confeſſion of ſinnes before God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 17.</note> The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woman (wherof Luke ſpeaketh) when ſhe came and beſought Ieſus to haue hir
<pb facs="tcp:8711:69"/> ſinnes forgiuen hir, ſhée wept: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, by this wéeping ſhe did not put away hir ſinne.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Geneſis.</hi> 27.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſau</hi> alſo wept, when <hi>Iacob</hi> had preuented him of his bleſſing: yet notwithſtanding, he did not therby put away his ſinne.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> And Chriſt ſayth: In the vtward partes there ſhall be wéeping and gnaſhing of téeth, and yet neuertheleſſe there ſhall be no ſatiſfaction there.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, the king commaundeth a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall faſt, ſaying: neyther man nor beaſt, ſhall taſte ought at all, neyther ſhall they féede or drinke water. But he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not a faſt, as though thereby ſinne ſhould be forgiuen, and the wrath of God pacified, as the hypocrytes imagine of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, but he commaunded it: firſt, to the ende the fleſhe might be brideled by ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then to the ende common banqueting might be omitted, whereby they myght more conueniently come togither to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique preaching and prayer. Wherevpon alſo it is added in the commaundement: let euery man cry mightily vnto God. Theſe are the publique prayers, or ſuffrages, which in ſolemne wiſe were obſerued and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8711:69"/> vſed of our elders not one houre, but the whole day. It were neceſſary therefore that men ſhould abſtaine from meate all the daye long, to the ende they might bée readie in the Church.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Para.</hi> 20.</note> So <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed a faſting, not to ſatiſfie thereby for ſinne, but for publique prayers ſake, which were appoynted to call vpon God in extréeme perill. So in many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſcripture, faſting and prayer are ioyned togither, to the ende wée might knowe that faſtings were appoynted as a preparatiue vnto prayer.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 But what meaneth the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giuen, for oxen, and ſhéepe,<note place="margin">The faſt of beaſtes.</note> and other beaſtes to faſt? Hath God reſpect vnto the faſting of beaſtes? There is nothing leſſe ment truely, but they are commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to faſt in that ſenſe and meaning, that beaſtes were commaunded in the lawe to haue reſt on the Sabboth day.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> Thou ſhalt doe no worke (ſayth the Lorde) on the Sabboth day, neyther thou, nor thy cattel, nor the ſtraunger that is within thy ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. For reſt is required of cattell, on the Sabboth day, that by that occaſion men
<pb facs="tcp:8711:70"/> might leaue off their ruſticall labors, and come togither about ſacred buſineſſe. So alſo, faſting is commaunded to oxen and ſhéepe, leaſt men being occupied in féeding their cattell, ſhould neglect and pretermit the publique prayers, and ſermons, which were then in <hi>Niniue,</hi> for the auoyding of the daunger which was at hande. For it was very néedefull for the <hi>Niniuets</hi> to be occupied in their publique temples, wyth prayers, with ſermons, with ſacrifices, and ſuche lyke ſeruices of God. Suche rite and cuſtome the primitiue Churche alſo imitated, after the Goſpell was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, and it is lawefull as yet in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tréeme perilles to imitate the ſame, ſo that it be not done hypocritically, papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically, and monaſtically, but godly, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, and chriſtianlye. The Papiſtes, and Monkes vſe theſe workes to the ende they might thereby merite remiſſion of their ſinnes. This is a deteſtable opinion, and farre from true repentaunce. But we muſt vſe theſe rightes and cuſtomes, to the ende we maye declare our ſelues to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to haue deſerued the wrath of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8711:70"/> God, and that we call now vpon the Lord for remiſſion of our ſinnes.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 This is alſo contayned in the Kinges commaundement. Let euerye man turne from his euill way, and from the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which he hath in hande. This is a ſermon of true repentance, and of the true fruites of repentance. For whereas before mention is made of ſackecloth, faſting, and aſhes, true repentaunce is not as yet declared, but only a ſigne of humilitie or confeſſion of ſinne. But nowe true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is taught, for it conſiſteth in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion from our euill way, and from the wickedneſſe which we haue in hande. But to be conuerted from iniquitie, is firſt to be conuerted from incredulitie, and from Idolatrie to the true fayth in Chriſt the ſonne of God. Furthermore, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted from iniquitie is to be turned from externall vices, to vertue, as from drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe to ſobrietie, from deceyte to true dealinge, from enuie to the loue of our neighbor, from whoredome to chaſtity: &amp; to be ſhort, from all kinde of wickedneſſe, to all maner of vertue. This is the meaning
<pb facs="tcp:8711:71"/> of the kinges commaundement when hée willed euery man to turne from his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked waye. And this is true repentaunce, which is alwayes required of vs.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Furthermore, in the commaundement, or proclamation of the king, this is alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Who can tell, whether God will turne, and repent, and ceaſe from hys fierce wrath that we periſhe not. What ſhall we ſaye to this? Doth the king doubt of the mercie of God, and of the remiſſion of ſinnes? Are we not commaunded cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to beléeue, and without doubting to be perſwaded, that God for Chriſtes ſake doth forgiue vs our ſinnes? and to the ende we ſhould firmely beléeue it in déede: ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ordeyned, as baptiſme, and the ſupper of the Lorde. Let vs therefore here note, that the king ſpeaketh not ſimplye of the remiſſion of ſinnes, when he ſayth, Who can tell whether God will turne, and repent, and ceaſe from his fierce wrath, and ſo forth, but includeth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of puniſhment, which <hi>IONAS</hi> prophecied ſhould come. For in the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinne, there is commonly a double
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8711:71"/> remiſſion, as the remiſſion of fault, and the remiſſion of puniſhment. By the Goſpel of Chriſt the remiſſion of fault is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and the remiſſion of puniſhment alſo. For Chriſt was promiſed vnto the elders, &amp; offered vnto vs, to take away our ſinne, &amp; to deliuer vs from the eternall torment of hell fire. Wherfore we muſt neuer doubt of this remiſſion, and if any doe doubt, hée reproueth Chriſt and his Goſpell of a lye.</p>
                  <p>But beſide the fault and eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the lawe of God threateneth to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, temporall and externe puniſhment alſo. As in this place, the <hi>Niniuets</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for their ſinnes eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the Prophete threatneth vnto them alſo, externall and worldlye puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which ſhould happen vnto them, and to their Citie within fortie dayes after. Neyther doth he adde the promiſe of the remiſſion of this externall puniſhment, if ſo be they ſhould be conuerted. Wherefore, the king although he could certainly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and appoint, that if they did certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent, their ſinnes ſhould be remitted, and they deliuered from eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb facs="tcp:8711:72"/> yet notwithſtanding, he coulde not certainlye affirme, or ſaye, whether God woulde forgiue for their repentaunce and conuerſion, the externall and worldly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. He commaundeth the people therefore to hope well, and to repent them trulye, bicauſe he being ſure that their ſinne ſhould be forgiuen, and they deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from hell, thought alſo that it might come to paſſe, that by the méere, frée, and vnpromiſed mercy of God, they might be deliuered from the ouerthrow and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Citie. So <hi>Dauid</hi> knewe that God had forgiuen him his ſinne, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered him from hell, but he knewe not whether he ſhoulde returne to his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Therefore he ſayth: If I ſhall finde fauour in the ſight of the Lorde, he will bring me againe, and ſhewe me both it and the tabernacle therof. But and if the Lord ſaye thus:<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 15.</note> I haue no luſt vnto thée, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde here I am, let him do with me what ſéemeth him good in his eyes.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Daniel.</hi> 3.</note> So the thrée yong men in the fierie Ouen, knewe not that they ſhould be deliuered from the fire, although they did not doubt of the grace of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8711:72"/> God in forgiuing their ſinne, and in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering them from hell. Therfore they ſay, our God whom we ſerue, is able to kéepe vs from the hote burning Ouen (O king) and can right well deliuer vs out of thy handes. And though he will not, yet ſhalt thou knowe, that we will not ſerue thy Gods, and ſo forth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ And when God ſawe their workes,<note place="margin">The text.</note> howe they turned from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wayes, he repented on the euill, which he ſayde he would doe vnto them, and did it not.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>This place the hypocrites doe abuſe, to defende the merites of humane righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And doe affirme that the wrath of God maye be pacified, and that ſinnes might be forgiuen for ſuch workes as are before mencioned, as by faſting, putting on of ſackecloth, and ſitting in duſt. But they greatly erre, and are deceyued. For firſt of all, the whole ende and ſcope of the Goſpell of Chriſt is to teach only that our ſinnes are forgiuen, and that the wrath of
<pb facs="tcp:8711:73"/> God is pacified for Chriſtes ſake, and by his death and paſſion, the which muſt bée acknowledged and comprehended by faith.</p>
                  <p>The pacifying therefore of the wrath of God, and the ſatiſfaction for ſinne before GOD, muſt not be attributed to anye of mans merites or deſerts, but to the mercie of God in Ieſus Chriſt. Furthermore, we haue ſhewed before, that faſting, and ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth of themſelues, are works indifferent and not acceptable vnto God, if ſo be they be done of wicked men, and of ſuch as are not reconciled vnto God. Wherevpon it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the prophecie of <hi>Eſay</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faſt we (ſay they) and thou ſéeſt it not?<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 58.</note> Beholde when ye faſt, your luſt remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſtill.</p>
                  <p>What meaneth then the text when it ſayth: God ſawe their workes? Thys ſcripture is not to be vnderſtoode of works which are done without repentaunce, but of the workes of true repentaunce: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it followeth in this place, howe euery man turned from his wicked way. This is the preaching and ſhewing forth of true repentaunce. For God in aſſwaging his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8711:73"/> wrath, and in forgiuing ſinnes, hath firſt of al reſpect vnto his only begotten ſonne, which hath ſatiſfied for ſinne, then he hath reſpect vnto them in whome he hath found his ſonne by faith. When as therfore they which beléeue in Chriſt, teſtifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of their ſinnes, by faſting and ſackcloth, and declare their fayth alſo by the amendement of their lyues, and by imbracing of vertue, then is God ſayde to haue reſpect vnto their workes, not that workes of themſelues are ſo meritorious, that for them God will turne awaye his wrath, but bicauſe works are arguments and certaine ſignes of the fayth which we haue in Chriſt Ieſus, whome God onely regardeth, and for whoſe merites alone he is pacified and forgiueth ſinnes. This now muſt be applied to the <hi>Niniuets.</hi> For the <hi>Niniuets</hi> were ſinners, &amp; for their ſinnes they deſerued to haue their Citie deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But at the preaching of <hi>IONAS</hi> they are terrified, and made beleue, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayd. But what did they beléeue? 1 Firſt, they beleued that God was angerie wyth them for their ſinnes, and that the worde
<pb facs="tcp:8711:74"/> which was preached vnto them as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the deſtruction of the Citie, was true, &amp; diuine. 2 Then they beleued that God was mercifull for the promiſed ſéede of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham:</hi> by the which fayth they faſted, and put on ſackcloth, to declare the true acknowledging of their ſinnes. 3 Laſt of all, they turned euerie one from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wayes to godlyneſſe and vertue, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their fayth and obedience towardes the ſéede of <hi>Abraham.</hi> God therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth their works, not for their merits, but for the ſéede of <hi>Abraham</hi> which was: Chriſt, whome they acknowledged by faith to be their only Sauiour &amp; redéemer.</p>
                  <p>And in this place we haue an excellent example, of howe great efficacie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, true repentance is. Many men thinke and déeme, that all thinges are done and come to paſſe by fatall deſtinie, that is, by a certaine neceſſitie, and immutable order of thinges. And therefore they count it vaine, to ſéeke meanes to auoide daungers to come, and to call vppon God to tourne away ſuch daungers as are at hande.</p>
                  <p>And truely it is moſt certaine that God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8711:74"/> is immutable,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iames.</hi> 1.</note> and without all ſhadowe of chaunge: I am God (ſayth he) and am not chaunged.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.</note> And the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth. They ſhall periſhe, but thou ſhalt endure. But as touching perils and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers at hand, God doth ſo determine them to come to paſſe, that if men doe repent, he receyueth them into his fauour, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth the puniſhment to come, and if not the temporall, yet at leaſt the puniſhment which is eternall. As the Lorde hymſelfe teſtifieth by the mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> ſaying. If that people repent them of their wickedneſſe, I alſo will repent me of the plague which I haue ſpoken.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 18.</note> Thys truely was ſpoken euen at the firſt, of the deſtruction of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to come, of the which <hi>Eſayas</hi> alſo prophecied long before. By the which ſaying is ſignified that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the purpoſe of God in hys threatninges, if men doe repent them of their ſinne, the Lorde alſo will turne from his wrath &amp; forgiue. The which thing the example of the <hi>Niniuets</hi> well prooueth: By whoſe example alſo <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned ſafe, if ſo be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citizens of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8711:75"/> had ſo repented at the preaching of <hi>Hieremy,</hi> as the <hi>Niniuets</hi> did at the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of <hi>IONAS.</hi> The like had happened to the Iewes, if they had afterwarde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, at the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as Chriſt himſelfe declareth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Hieruſalem, Hieruſalem,</hi> how often would I haue gathered thée,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 23.</note> euen as the Hen gathereth hir Chickings vnder hir winges, and ye woulde not. And againe: There ſhall no ſigne be giuen vnto them,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 12.</note> but the ſigne of <hi>IONAS</hi> in the Whales belly. God truely, is ſo delighted in repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, that if the wicked doe but repent him externally, although he forgiue not his ſinne, &amp; remit not his eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: yet notwithſtanding, he wil forgiue ſome part, of his externe and temporall puniſhement in this worlde: as teſtifieth the example of <hi>Achab,</hi> the wickedneſſe of whoſe heart, although it remayned ſtill: yet neuertheleſſe, when he humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at the preaching of <hi>Elias,</hi> and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted externally, God was ſo delighted ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with that the puniſhment was deferred to the poſteritie of <hi>Achab.</hi> Wherfore if any
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8711:75"/> man deſire to haue not onely the temporal puniſhment in this worlde for ſinne, but alſo the euerlaſting puniſhmente in the worlde to come, remitted. Let him repent truely, that is, let hym acknowledge hys ſinne, let him beleue in Chriſt, and let him ſhewe true obedience towardes God. So God graunted a hundred &amp; twentie yeres ſpace of repentaunce before the floud. So that if they had repented at the preaching of <hi>Noe,</hi> they had not onely eſcaped the puniſhment of the flood, but alſo the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hell fyre. So God gaue foure hundred yeres ſpace of repentaunce to the Gentiles, the <hi>Cananites,</hi> ſo to <hi>Pharao,</hi> ſo alſo in theſe dayes to vs, in the which, the Turke threateneth to vs Chriſtians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: I ſay he hath giuen vs ſpace of repentaunce, to the which, he calleth vs by the preaching of his holy Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>If therefore we repent vs truly, that is, if we faithfully and vnfeynedlye imbrace the Goſpell, and amend our liues publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and priuately, generally and perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, from the hyeſt to the loweſt, then we ſhall eſcape the puniſhment and tyrannie
<pb facs="tcp:8711:76"/> of the Turke, Pope, and all the enimies of God. But for ſo much as the contempt of the Goſpell is great, and the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of lyfe alſo verye much, as in drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, deceyte, whoredome, ſwearing, and in manye other vices, it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that we ſhall not eſcape vnpuniſhed. Wherfore, let vs all generally with one conſent pray vnto God, that he wil vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe ſo to kindle our hartes with his holye ſpirite, that we maye amende our liues, and ſo be deliuered from all thoſe plagues which are at hande.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">The text.</note>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herefore IONAS was ſore diſcontent, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry. And he prayed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde, and ſayd: O Lord, was not this my ſaying (I pray thee) when I was yet in my countrie? Therefore I haſted rather to flie vnto Tharſis. For I knowe well ynough that thou art a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8711:76"/> mercifull God, full of compaſsion, long ſuffering, and of great kindneſſe, and repenteſt when thou ſhouldeſt take puniſhment. And nowe, O Lorde I beſeeche thee, take my life from me, for I had rather die than liue. Then ſayde the Lorde: art thou ſo angrye? And IONAS gat him out of the City, and ſate downe on the eaſt ſide therof: and there made him a booth, and ſate vnder it, in the ſhadowe, till he might ſee what ſhould chaunce vnto the city.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>HItherto we haue ſpoken of the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the <hi>Niniuets:</hi> and nowe wée muſt ſay ſomwhat of the indignation and diſpleaſure which <hi>IONAS</hi> tooke at the repentance and conſeruation of the <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets.</hi> For after that <hi>IONAS</hi> ſawe that the <hi>Niniuets</hi> at his preaching, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto the Lorde, and had obteyned not only remiſſion of their ſinnes, but alſo the ſafegarde of the Citie, he ſhould great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue reioyced,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> euen as the Aungels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce more, ouer one ſinner that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, than ouer ninetie and nine that are
<pb facs="tcp:8711:77"/> righteous: but he is ſo farre from reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that he rather taketh indignation and diſpleaſure with him ſelfe, and inuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with his complaint agaynſt the Lorde our God, for ſparing them. For he ſayth, O Lorde was not this my ſaying I praye thée when I was yet in my countrie? By the which expoſtulation and complaint, he caſteth God in the téeth with his excéeding mercie, and long ſufferance, and accuſeth him of iniuſtice, and vnrighteouſneſſe. And alſo he ſorroweth ſo much for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce and preſeruation of the <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets,</hi> that he wiſheth death vnto himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Although many men were woont to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the faultes of holy men, and to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete them to the beſt: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, bicauſe this déede and this indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>IONAS</hi> is reprehended of God himſelfe (as hereafter ſhall appeare) ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not lawfull for vs, vainelye to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe this ſinne of the Prophete.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 4.</note> Charitie truly bindeth vs to couer the ſinnes of our neyghbours ſo much as we may. But yet we may not make righteouſneſſe of ſinne, neyther muſt we ſay that ſinne is equitie,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8711:77"/> and equitie, ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IONAS</hi> therefore in this, ſinneth once againe, bicauſe he is offended at the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and preſeruation of the <hi>Niniuets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He ſéemeth trulye to himſelfe to haue iuſt cauſe of indignation. For firſt of all, when God ſpared the <hi>Niniuets: IONAS</hi> thought that the worde of God which he preached, was in daunger of diſcredit. For he had ſayd it would come to paſſe within fortie dayes that <hi>Niniue</hi> ſhoulde bée ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne. The which thing, when it came not to paſſe according to his prophecie, who would afterward beléeue the worde of the Lorde? who would beléeue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, if God fulfill not the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of his worde? who woulde not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the Prophetes of vanitie and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? <hi>IONAS</hi> therefore thought that it woulde be to the glorie of Gods name to haue the Citie of <hi>Niniue</hi> deſtroyed. The which, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it came not to paſſe, he thought that the glorye of Gods name was in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarde and perill. Furthermore, when he ſaw the <hi>Niniuets</hi> which were Ethnickes and vncircumciſed, to obtayne remiſſion
<pb facs="tcp:8711:78"/> of ſinnes, and to be receyued into gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, he thought that the lawe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and Circumciſion, was in great perill, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Ethnicks when they ſhould heare that god without reſpect of perſons, receiueth thoſe that truly repent (although they were vncircumciſed) woulde ſaye by and by, what auayleth Circumciſion? what profite ſhall the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> bring vnto vs, when theſe being Ethnickes, are receyued without Circumciſion, and the lawe of <hi>Moſes</hi> into Gods fauour? <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> iudged theſe things to be moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt. Fearing therefore leaſt by the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of God, the truth of his worde, the glorie of Circumciſion, and the lawe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhoulde be in daunger of diſcredit, he taketh ſuch indignation at the matter, that he wiſheth death vnto himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>IONAS</hi> (I ſaye) greatly erred. For as touching the preſeruation of the truth of Gods worde, God in ſparing the <hi>Niniuets,</hi> truly fulfilled the truth of his worde. For although it were ſayd: There are yet fortie dayes, and then ſhall <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue</hi> be ouerthrowne: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8711:78"/> (as it is ſayde before) this is ſo to be vnderſtoode, that <hi>Niniue</hi> ſhall be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, if the Citizens of the ſame did not repent. But and if they repent, then ſhall the Citie abide in ſafetie. For, that this is the meaning of Gods threatnings, thoſe wordes and Epithytes, which <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> himſelfe in this place rehearſeth, declare. For if God be gentle, mercifull, and long ſuffering, he will willinglye, no doubt, forgiue the ſinnes of thoſe that turn vnto him, as appeareth by the mouth of <hi>Ezechiell,</hi> I will not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but rather that hée turne from his wickedneſſe, and liue. Wherefore <hi>IONAS</hi> feared in vaine, that God in ſparing the <hi>Niniuets,</hi> ſhoulde loſe the credit and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of his worde.</p>
                  <p>And as touching the Circumciſion, and lawe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which ſéeme to be aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, bicauſe God receiued the <hi>Niniuets</hi> into his fauour without thoſe: <hi>IONAS</hi> declareth agayne his ignorance. For Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and the lawe of <hi>Moſes</hi> (ſo farre as it conteyneth the ceremoniall and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall rightes) pertayne not to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,
<pb facs="tcp:8711:79"/> but onely to the externe poſteritie of <hi>Abraham.</hi> And God is not onely the God of the Iewes, but alſo the God of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. For although the Iewes only, had a promiſe that Chriſt ſhoulde ſpring out of their nation: yet notwithſtanding the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was not ſo made vnto them, that they alone ſhoulde obteyne ſaluation by Chriſt, but as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſayeth: amonge all people whoſo calleth vpon the name of the Lord, is acceptable vnto him. And againe: Euery one which calleth vppon the name of the Lorde ſhall be ſaued. Wherefore, <hi>IONAS</hi> once againe falleth into a foule errour.</p>
                  <p>Here therefore beholde and ſée, with how great feare of God euery man ought to walke in his vocation, and neuer to turne awaye his eyes from Gods holye worde. This <hi>IONAS</hi> was a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, which by inſpiration of the holye ghoſt prophecied of many thinges, and by his prophecie reſtored the kingdome of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell,</hi> with whome alſo it pleaſed God to talk. And yet when he was left to his own ſtrength, and turned away his eyes from
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8711:79"/> the worde of the Lord, he greatly erred in the vnderſtanding of the law and the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. He vnderſtandeth not the true ſenſe and meaning of the law, namely, that the lawe bringeth not death but to impenitent perſons onely. He vnderſtandeth not the condicion of Chriſt, namely, that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to all nations, which by fayth in him, repent them of their ſinnes. Therfore let vs not be prowde of our gifts, but let vs walke in the feare of the Lorde, and perſiſt in his calling, let vs be thankefull to God for his benifits, leaſt by our ingratitude he take them from vs. This is alſo to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that we muſt not truſt to our good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions (as ſome terme them) but wée muſt direct all our doings by the worde of God. <hi>IONAS</hi> in thys his indignation and diſpleaſure, hath (as ſéemeth vnto him) a verye good intention and meaning, he perſwadeth himſelfe to haue iuſt cauſes of offence, but when they are examined by the worde of God, they ſhall be found ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtlye repugnaunt agaynſt the ſame. Wherevpon it is ſayde in <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> that no man ſhall doe that which ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:8711:80"/> right to be done in his owne eyes. let vs take héede therefore, in all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that we take nothing in hande, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the calling of the worde of God.</p>
                  <p>But the titles and Epithytes of God which <hi>IONAS</hi> here rehearſeth, are not to be pretermitted. For although he reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth theſe, to reaſon and argue with God: yet notwithſtanding, they are moſt true and taken out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bookes of <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Numeri,</hi> which are ſet forth before our eyes, to the ende we maye learne to know what affection god beareth vnto vs, and what opinion we ought to haue of him.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2:</note>1 <hi>A mercifull God.</hi> This title, God attributeth to himſelfe in all places of the ſcripture, to the ende we might knowe his nature, that although he be ſometimes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, yet notwithſtanding he is not angry to deſtroy, but to ſaue all thoſe that hope and call vppon him.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28.</note> He is angry (ſayth the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi>) to the ende he might be mercifull, he maketh deade to the ende he might reuiue. This tytle (if we well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of the ſame) confirmeth our fayth in all aduerſitie. And fayth is the obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8711:80"/> of the firſt commaundement. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this title being well knowne, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs to obey the firſt and ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Full of compaſsion.</hi> This title pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly pertayneth to naturall beneuolence, ſuch as we ſée commonly in parentes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their children. The mother ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth hir children, that for their payne ſhe ſorroweth euen at the very heart, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth (if it might be poſſible) for the eaſe of hir childe, to féele the ſame hir ſelfe. Such, and farre greater, is the mercy of god towardes his afflicted Church. He is not ſimplye ſorye for it, but hée is ſorie in heart and minde: yea (if I may ſo ſpeake) he yerneth in the bowels of his mercye. This tytle of God being well knowne, worketh in our hearts by the holy ghoſt, pacience in trouble, and affliction.</p>
                  <p>For if God be ſorye for our euill and harme, euen as the mother is ſorye for hir childe, it cannot be that euils (whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be) ſhall oppreſſe vs. For God will not ſuffer vs to periſhe in them, but will make a way euen in the verie midſt
<pb facs="tcp:8711:81"/> for vs to eſcape.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Long ſuffering.</hi> Thys title teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs the feare of God, that we flatter not our ſelues in our ſinnes. For God wynketh at ſinners, not that he doth alow their ſinnes, but bicauſe he looketh for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce. Wherfore if they repent, they are ſaued. If they be impenitent, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a iuſt reward for the ſame. Knoweſt thou not, (ſayth ſaint <hi>Paule</hi>) that the long ſufferaunce of the Lorde leadeth thée to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce. This place alſo teacheth vs pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience in aduerſitie. For whereas it doth not at the firſt puniſh thoſe which doe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt or trouble vs, it commeth ſo to paſſe, bicauſe he is long ſuffering, the which ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue we ought to imitate, and paciently to looke for helpe at hys handes.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Of great kindeneſſe.</hi> That is, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding benificiall, and liberall. For God is not onely mercifull, louing, and kinde in heart, but alſo he teſtifieth the ſame, by many benifites beſtowed vpon vs. And he beſtoweth in déede more, and greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifits vpon vs, than eyther we can or dare aſke at his handes. Wherefore let vs not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8711:81"/> diſpaire in aduerſitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶ And the Lorde God prepared a wilde Vine:<note place="margin">The Text.</note> which ſprang vp ouer IONAS, that he might haue ſhadow ouer his head, to delyuer him out of his paine. And IONAS was exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glad of the wilde Vine.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IONAS</hi> being gone out of the citie, after his ſermon, waited that he might ſée wyth his eyes, what happened to the Citie. But when he perceiued in déede his expectation to be fruſtrate, and that it came farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to paſſe than he looked for, and that all thinges prooued contrarye to his preaching, he was greatly vexed &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in minde, as we haue ſhewed before.</p>
                  <p>But in the meane ſeaſon, whyle <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS</hi> behelde what ſhoulde happen, he is greatly troubled in the fielde with the heat of the Sunne, in ſo much that he deſireth to die in ſo great affliction, rather than to lyue any longer. For although <hi>IONAS</hi> had made him a Boothe, (peraduenture of ſuch boughes and ſhrubs as came next to
<pb facs="tcp:8711:82"/> hande) yet notwithſtanding this Boothe, could not ſo ſhadow him from the beames of the ſunne, but that he might be parched with the ſame. Wherefore, the Lorde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him a wylde Vine, with the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe wherof, <hi>IONAS</hi> was ſo refreſhed, that he greatly reioyced. Firſt of all ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here note, that where as the Boothe, which <hi>IONAS</hi> builte, holpe him nothing at al, neyther defended him from the heate of the Sunne, it is plainely ſet forth vnto vs, that humane ſtudies, pollicies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, doe helpe vs nothing at all in our great temptations and afflictions.</p>
                  <p>For although our indeuors (if ſo be they be godly and done with a good conſcience) are not in aduerſitie to be omitted, but all godlye, iuſte, right, lawfull, and honeſt meanes are to be vſed, leaſt God be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: yet notwithſtanding, neceſſitie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayneth vs that when we haue done all that euer we can, not to truſt vnto the ſame, but onely to depend vpon the Lorde our God, and to beſéeche him that he will vouchſafe to proſper, and giue good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto our indeuor. We ought alwaies
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8711:82"/> to haue in minde <hi>Peters</hi> fiſhing,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 5.</note> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing labored all the night in vaine to take fiſhe, and letting ſlip againe his Nets to make a draught at the commaundement of Chriſt, incloſed a great multitude of fiſhes.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 8.</note> The woman likewiſe which was diſeaſed with an iſſue of bloud a long time, and ſpent all hir goodes vpon Phiſitions to be cured, and could not: yet neuertheleſſe afterwarde by the onely worde of Chriſt, ſhe receyued preſent remedie and health. So <hi>IONAS</hi> alſo was nothing holpen by his Booth, which he made himſelfe, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the Lord had cauſed a wilde Vine to growe ouer him, he was not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended from the heate of the Sunne, but alſo he was greatly refreſhed, and filled with ioy. Theſe things are not ſpoken to the ende we ſhoulde be negligent or ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in our vocation, and careleſſe in doing our duetie: (For we ought to leaue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnaſſayed in perils and daungers, which maye be done godly, honeſtly, and lawfully.) But theſe things are ſpoken to this ende, that when by our induſtry we haue prouided all thinges neceſſarie, we
<pb facs="tcp:8711:83"/> may yet know that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> help of God is moſt neceſſarie, and that we ought to call for the ſame by prayer. According to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Prophete <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.</note> Except the Lord kéepe the Citie, the watch man wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth but in vaine. Furthermore, where as God in ſo great trouble of heate prepared a wylde Vine for <hi>IONAS,</hi> by the ſhadow whereof he was recreated, we learne that God is of ſo great clemencie and louing kindeneſſe, that ſo many as walke in hys vocation and are afflicted in the ſame, ſhal receyue at his handes a meane to indure the ſame, according to the Pſalmiſt, The Sunne ſhal not burne thée by day,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.</note> neither the Moone by night. Alſo it is ſayde, Who ſo dwelleth vnder the defence of the moſt higheſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.</note> ſhall abide vnder the ſhadow of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almightie. Further it is ſayd, A thouſand ſhall fall beſide thée, &amp; ten thouſand at thy right hand, but it ſhall not come nigh thée.</p>
                  <p>And the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſayth, if thou walke thorow fyre,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 43.</note> it ſhall not burne thée. So, the children of Iſraell went out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into the deſert, for although there was not corne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſert: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8711:83"/> God brought to paſſe that they might beare it, bicauſe he ſent them <hi>Manna,</hi> and gaue them water out of the rock. <hi>Hieremy</hi> walked in the calling of God, when he propheſied of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtruction of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for the which he was caſt not onely into priſon, but alſo into the mire, to the ende he might ſéeme to periſhe with hunger. But God made him able to beare it, and wrought meanes by his friendes to dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him, and to ſet him at libertie.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtles were ſent out to preache the Goſpell throughout the whole worlde, but wythout prouiſion: God therefore brought to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they hauing nothing, poſſeſſed all things. Theſe ſayings and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Scripture are ſet downe vnto vs to this ende, that although we muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer great perils in the vocation wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God hath called vs: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, we muſt go forward voyde of feare, hauing a certaine hope, that he will dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶But vpon the next morow,<note place="margin">The Text.</note> againſt the ſpring of the day, the Lord or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned
<pb facs="tcp:8711:84"/> a worme, which ſmote the wylde Vine, ſo that it withered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And when the Sunne was vp, God prepared a feruent eaſt wind: and the Sunne bet ouer the heade of IONAS, that he faynted againe, and wiſhed vnto his ſoule that hee might dye, and ſayde: it is better for me to die than to liue.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IONAS</hi> is refreſhed and recreated with the ſhadowe of the wylde Vine, but hys ioye laſteth not long, bicauſe the wylde Vine is by and by ſtriken with a worme, that it periſheth: and <hi>IONAS</hi> againe is ſo greatly afflicted that he wyſheth death vnto himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>This is a liuely Image and ſpectacle, of the variety, alteration, and chaunge of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane thinges in thys worlde. And yet notwithſtanding, we muſt conſider that this alteration was not raſhely brought to paſſe, but by the iuſte and wiſe councell of God.</p>
                  <p>At the firſt <hi>IONAS</hi> reioyced for the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of the Vine, nowe he ſorroweth for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8711:84"/> the deſtruction of the ſame. Such is the courſe and raſe of mans life. One while he reioyceth bicauſe of proſperitye, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while he lamenteth bicauſe of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. And yet notwithſtanding theſe things come not to paſſe by hap or by chance, but by the ordinaunce of God. For in that the wylde Vine periſhed, and <hi>IONAS</hi> thereby brought into great ſorrowe and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God had a ſecret meaning. For he ment thereby to teache <hi>IONAS,</hi> that if he ſorrowed ſo much for the deſtruction of a wylde Vine, for the which he neuer labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: how much more ſhoulde God be ſory for the deſtruction of ſo great a Citie as <hi>Niniue</hi> was, of the which he was the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and gouernour, and how much more ſhould he ſpare ſo great a multitude. Let vs learne therfore by this place, that God doth neuer caſt vs into any ſorrowe or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, but that he meaneth to teache vs ſomewhat, as to prooue our faith,<note place="margin">The ende of affliction</note> to ſtirre vs vp to repentance, or elſe to ſet forth the glorie of his name.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, this is not to be pretermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that <hi>IONAS</hi> ſo often wiſheth death
<pb facs="tcp:8711:85"/> vnto himſelfe, when as he greatly feared death, before he was ſwallowed vp of the Whale. Here againe, the inconſtancie of man is plainely ſet forth vnto vs. Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I wiſhe for death (ſayth the Poet) and oftentimes I refuſe it agayne. So <hi>Elias,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>Kings.</hi> 19.</note> one whyle fléeth death, and another whyle wiſheth for the ſame. This incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of mans nature is diligently to bée noted euen in the holyeſt men, not that we ought to alowe or excuſe the ſame, but bicauſe it is our dueties to correct and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende the like in our ſelues. We can not put from vs all feare of death, neyther can we let or ceaſe to wyſhe for death in great aduerſitie. But we muſt ſpecially beware leaſt wée diſpaire in the feare of death, whereas we ought to haue a ſure truſt in Chriſt, and to ſuffer death with a valyant minde. Alſo we muſt beware, leaſt in wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing for death, we bring death to oure ſelues, but rather we muſt perſiſt in our vocation, hauing a ſure hope that although we be beſet with daunger, on euerie ſide, God will make away in the midſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhall eſcape.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:8711:85"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>¶And God ſayde vnto IONAS:<note place="margin">The text.</note> art thou ſo angry for the wilde Vine? And he ſayde, yea verie angry am I, euen vnto the death. And the Lorde ſayde thou haſt compaſsion vpon a wylde Vine, whereon thou beſtowedſt no labor, nor madeſt it growe, which ſprang vp in one night, &amp; periſhed in another: And ſhoulde not I then haue compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon Niniue that great Citie, wherein there are about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred &amp; twenty thouſande perſons, that knowe not their right hande fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their left, beſids much cattell?</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>God prepared (as we hearde before) a wylde Vine for <hi>IONAS,</hi> that vnder the ſhadowe of it, he might be defended from the heate of the ſunne. This wylde Vine being withered, <hi>IONAS</hi> was full of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and wrath. The Lorde therfore reprehendeth his wrath, and declareth for what cauſe he brought to paſſe that the wylde Vine ſhould ſpring vp in one night and vaniſh away agayne in another. For
<pb facs="tcp:8711:86"/> before, when <hi>IONAS</hi> ſawe that God did ſpare the <hi>Niniuets,</hi> he tooke it grieuouſlye that the Lorde ſhoulde ſhew ſuch clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie towardes them, and was greatly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry. Now therfore the Lord teacheth <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS,</hi> howe vniuſt, vncharitable, and cruell his anger is, by a compariſon of the wilde Vine. Thou art ſorye (ſayth he) for the wilde Vine, which thou haſt not made to growe, and ſhoulde not I be ſorie, and ſpare ſo great a Citie which firſt of all by my benediction is come to ſo great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and by the benifites which I haue beſtowed vppon them is at this time the monarchie of the whole worlde? In the which Citie alſo there are ſo manye thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of infants and yong children, which as yet are not come to the age of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, beſides thouſandes of cattell which neuer did harme.</p>
                  <p>We haue therefore here an example of that ſaying, which is in S. <hi>Paules</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> where it is ſayde, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible things of God, are knowne by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible creatures. But among all creatures, the naturall affections of men are ſpoken
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8711:86"/> of. For we ſpeake not of corrupt or vicious affections, as of pride, of enuie, of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, of crueltie, of deſiring other mens goods, or ſuch like, which are ſinnes, the author wherof is Sathan, and not god. But we ſpeake of the affections of men, which God by nature hath ingraffed in vs. Of the which affections, one is, to be ſorie if any thing profitable proſper not, but periſhe: as in this place, <hi>IONAS</hi> is ſory that the Vine, (a thing very profitable for him) ſhould ſo ſodenly periſhe. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this affection was not in <hi>IONAS</hi> without ſinne: yet notwithſtanding, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of it ſelfe was not ſinne. So the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>Elizeus</hi> was ſory, bicauſe his Axe being a thing profitable to cut woode,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Kings.</hi> 6.</note> fell into the water. This affection is naturall, not ſprong vp in our fleſh by chaunce, but by the wiſedome and ſecret councell of god created &amp; ingraffed in vs. What then doe we learne by this? Surely by this ſenſible affection in vs we learne and are admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of the inſenſible and inuiſible affection of God towarde vs. For if we greatly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe for things loſt and deſtroyed, which
<pb facs="tcp:8711:87"/> we notwithſtanding neyther created nor made, let vs vnderſtande and knowe that the Lorde doth much more ſorrow for men which he hath created, and for whoſe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation he hath ſent his onely begotten ſonne into the worlde to ſuffer death.</p>
                  <p>Wherevpon by the mouth of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, he ſweareth, ſaying, I liue, and will not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he turne from his wickedneſſe, and liue. So in the nine and fortie Chapter of <hi>Eſay,</hi> he teacheth vs to knowe the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and loue which he beareth towards vs by the affection of a mother towardes hir childe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 49.</note> ſaying: Can the mother forget hir childe that ſhe bare, and not pitie the ſonne of hir owne fleſhe? And though ſhée doe forget, yet will I not forget thée. So, alſo, he propoundeth his loue before vs to be knowne by the affection of a father to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his ſonne in the .xj. Chapter of ſaint Luke, ſaying: Which of you being a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 11.</note> of whom if the ſonne ſhal aſke bread, will giue him a ſtone? If ye then being euill can giue good thinges vnto your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, how much more ſhall your father of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8711:87"/> heauen giue the holye ſpirite to thoſe that deſire it of him. So lykewiſe in the fiftene of Luke,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 15.</note> by the Parable of the houſholder which ſorowed for the loſſe of his ſheepe, and by the Parable of the loſt groate, is ſet forth vnto vs the excéeding loue of God towardes loſt men, that is, towardes ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that they might be brought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and ſaluation. Wherefore our affections are ordeined of God to be dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall preachers vnto vs, and to teach vs how God is affectioned towardes vs, and to make vs féele the affections of God, which otherwiſe are inſenſible, and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, when as it is ſayde that God ſpared, and had compaſſion vpon the Citie of <hi>Niniue</hi> for ſo many thouſands of men, which knewe not their right hande from their left, there are diuers expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Some expounde thoſe that knewe not their right hande from their left, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes and children: Otherſome thereby vnderſtande the common and ſimple ſort of people. But the firſt opinion is beſt allowed, namelye, that they were
<pb facs="tcp:8711:88"/> children, as yet not come to age of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Notwithſtanding we muſt not think that God ſpared thoſe infants and children for their innocencie: (for although chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and infants be innocents before men: yet they are not innocents before god, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are conceyued and borne in ſinne.) But he ſpared them for two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. The firſt is, bicauſe he is gentle and mercifull. It is neyther (ſayth S. <hi>Paule</hi>) in the willer nor in the runner, but in the mercie of god. <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo eryed and ſayd, Lorde, Lorde God, mercifull, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, long ſuffering, and abundaunt in goodneſſe and truth, and kéeping mercy in ſtore for thouſandes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.</note> forgiuing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vngodlyneſſe, and ſinne, and not leauing one innocent, viſiting the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of fathers vpon the children. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond cauſe why God ſpared the Innocents was, for that the auncient men of the Citie (though not all, yet the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part) repented at the preaching of <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAS.</hi> God therefore ſpared the Infants, for the elders ſake which repented: As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by that which he ſayth in another
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8711:88"/> place thus:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.</note> Shewing mercie vnto thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes in them that loue me, and kéepe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements. For as God was woont to deſtroy children and Infantes, for the wickedneſſe of their forefathers (as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the time of the floode, in the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and in the ouerthrowing of the <hi>Amalekyts</hi>) So he was wont to ſpare, bleſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 15.</note> and preſerue Infants for the godlyneſſe of their forefathers and elders. Wherefore if Parentes wiſhe well vnto their children, and woulde beſtowe great benifits vpon their children, they ſhall not néede to ſcrape great aboundaunce of ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes togither, for God will bleſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for them, if ſo be that Parents them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues liue godly, and vertuouſly in their vocation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Laſt of all wheras he addeth, <hi>Beſide much cattell:</hi> We may not thinke that it is ſpoken, as though God ſpared ſuch a Citie for the brute beaſtes ſake, and that he ſo much regarded them. It cannot bée denyed, but that God after a certaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath a care ouer beaſtes and cattell: As we may reade in the lawe where it is
<pb facs="tcp:8711:89"/> ſayde. In the Saboth day thou ſhalt doe no maner of worke, neyther thou, nor thy ſonne, nor thy daughter (and in the ende he addeth) neyther thy cattell that is within thy gates. And in the hundred and fourth Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.145.147.</note> it is ſaid, he bringeth forth graſſe for the cattell. Yet notwithſtanding, God ſpareth not men for the cattles ſake, but he ſpareth the cattell for the mens ſake. As we may read, that the beaſts of the earth are deſtroyed for the ſinnes of men, as in the floode, in <hi>Sodome,</hi> in <hi>Amelecke:</hi> So alſo we may reade that beaſtes were and are preſerued for the godlineſſe of men, as in the .xxviij.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deutr.</hi> 28.</note> Chapter of <hi>Deutronomy.</hi> If thou ſhalt harken vnto the voyce of the Lorde thy God. Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the towne, and bleſſed in the fieldes: bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall be the fruite of thy body, and the fruite of thy ground, and the fruite of thy cattell, the increaſe of thine oxen, and the flockes of thy ſhéepe. &amp;c. Wherefore who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou be, that wilt haue thy cattell, thy goodes, and ſubſtance preſerued, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and increaſed, thou ſhalt not néede to vſe ſorceries, nor Witchcraftes, but ſée
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8711:89"/> that thou thy ſelfe be godly, and that thou perſeuer in thy calling, ſo ſhalt thou bée ſure and ſafe in the lande: ſo ſhall God bleſſe thée and thy poſteritie for euer.</p>
                  <p>This we haue paſſed ouer the Hiſtorie of <hi>IONAS,</hi> in the which there are many things to be obſerued and noted, but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally theſe. Firſt in <hi>IONAS,</hi> we haue an example of the infirmitie and weakeneſſe of all men, and euen of thoſe which are the holyeſt, and the ſaintes of God, for we ſée the diſobedience of <hi>IONAS,</hi> his terrors, and feares in the Whales belly, his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation alſo and griefe at the repentaunce of the <hi>Niniuets.</hi> But notwithſtanding, bicauſe he obeyed the calling of the Lorde, and perſeuered in the ſame, he is miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſaued, and preſerued.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all, we haue an example of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce in the <hi>Niniuets:</hi> by the which we are admoniſhed that although we grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly offend the diuine maieſtie of God, whereby we deſerue euerlaſting deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yet notwithſtanding, we ought not to diſpaire of our ſaluation, but rather repent vs truely, and vnfaynedly of our ſinnes.
<pb facs="tcp:8711:90"/> For the gate of heauen alwayes ſtandeth open to receyue penitent ſinners. And Chriſt himſelfe ſtandeth in the ſame, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynually inuiting, and calling ſuche vnto him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 11.</note> ſaying. Come vnto me all ye that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and are heauie laden, and I will eaſe you. Wherefore, to him with the father and the holy ghoſt, thrée perſons, and omnipotent, immortall, wiſe, and inuiſible God, be all honor, praiſe, glory, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, nowe and for euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Repent Englande in time,</l>
                  <l>as Niniue that Citie did:</l>
                  <l>For that thy ſinnes before the Lorde,</l>
                  <l>are not in ſecret hid.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8711:90"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
